<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christianity, the great mystery in answer to a late treatise, Christianity not mysterious, that is, not above, not contrary to reason : in opposition to which is asserted Christianity is above created reason in its pure estate and contrary to humane reason as fallen and corrupted, and therefore, in proper sense mystery : together with a post[s]cript letter to the author on his second edition enlarg'd / by T.B.</title>
            <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 162 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A27589</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B2131</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12817</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11696639</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11696639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A27589)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 14:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christianity, the great mystery in answer to a late treatise, Christianity not mysterious, that is, not above, not contrary to reason : in opposition to which is asserted Christianity is above created reason in its pure estate and contrary to humane reason as fallen and corrupted, and therefore, in proper sense mystery : together with a post[s]cript letter to the author on his second edition enlarg'd / by T.B.</title>
                  <author>Beverley, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Toland, John, 1670-1722. Christianity not mysterious.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 56 [i.e. 60] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for W. Marshal ... and John Marshall ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dondon [i.e. London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christianity --  Essence, genius, nature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CHRISTIANITY <hi rend="blackletterType">The Great Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN ANSWER to a late Treatiſe, Chriſtianity not Myſterious: THAT IS Not Above, Not Contrary to Reaſon.</p>
            <p>In oppoſition to which is Aſſerted, Chriſtianity is above Created Reaſon, in its pure Eſtate.</p>
            <p>And contrary to Humane Reaſon, as Fallen and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted: and therefore in proper ſenſe, Myſtery.</p>
            <p>Together with a <hi>Poſtcript</hi> Letter to the Author, on his Second Edition Enlarg'd.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>W. Marſhal</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Newgate-Street:</hi> And <hi>John Marſhall</hi> at the Bible in <hi>Grace-Church-ſtreet.</hi> 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:173120:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173120:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Truly Chriſtian Readers.</head>
            <p>I Have (I hope through the Grace of God) with a ſincere <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Zeal,</hi> deſired to Argue for the Glory of the Truths of the Goſpel, under the Honourable Title of <hi>Myſteries,</hi> (as they were, <hi>once for All, delivered to the Saints,</hi>) according to the beſt Methods of Diſcuſſion, and Ratiocinative Debate from Scripture Reaſon: But behold, I firſt <hi>ſhew to my ſelf, and to you,</hi> a more <hi>Excellent,</hi> or <hi>Tranſcendent way:</hi> That is, <hi>Receiving the love of Truth,</hi> or <hi>Truth in the Love of it;</hi> and with thoſe mighty Energies, and Efficacies of it upon the Heart and Life. <hi>David</hi> obſerving <hi>Men making void the Law,</hi> that is, the whole Doctrine of God in his word, was Holily Enflam'd upon it; <hi>Therefore I love thy Commandments above Gold, yea, above Fine Gold; Therefore I eſteem All thy Precepts concerning All Things to be Right; and I hate every falſe way.</hi> The beſt Antidote againſt the Poyſon of an Infecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Air, or Age is the inward Experimental Senſe, that <hi>God hath choſen us to Salvation, through Sanctification of the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Belief of the Truth.</hi> The moſt diſtinguiſhing Teſt of Truth, that it is of God, is ſelf-Reſignation and Obedience <hi>in doing the Will of God;</hi> The Witneſs of the Father, the Word, the Spirit, when we have it in our Selves, can alone enable us to ſet our Seal to that Truth; The <hi>Conſcience purged from dead Works to ſerve the Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God, by the Blood Offer'd by the Eternal Spirit; and the Blood of the Everlaſting covenant, making perfect in every Good Work to do his Will, and working in us, what is well pleaſing in his Sight,</hi> are the moſt Aſſuring Seals of the Eternal Godhead of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſuch an <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Time; <hi>The Gates of Hell,</hi> All the Reaſon, Policy, Wit, Authority of it, cannot prevail againſt a Chriſtian ſo founded on that <hi>Rock:</hi> The <hi>Work of Faith with Power,</hi> according to that Hiſtory of Believers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. does above All, diſplay the
<pb facs="tcp:173120:3"/> Myſterious Efficacy of it, which none <hi>know,</hi> but <hi>they who have it.</hi> That it gives a preſence of its Objects above all, that Sence can do, of its proper Objects; and a Demonſtration of its <hi>Idea</hi>'s, above all that <hi>Reaſon</hi> is Able for; For it can prevail Above both, when they would carry contrary to its Scope and End, and Impowers to Action far above them, by vertue of that <hi>Hypostaſis,</hi> and thoſe its <hi>Demonſtrations:</hi> Let us therefore <hi>Bow our Knees</hi> mutually, that <hi>the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt</hi> would grant us, according to the <hi>Riches of his Glory,</hi> to be <hi>ſtrengthen'd by his Spirit in the Inner Man,</hi> that <hi>Chriſt may dwell in our Hearts by Faith;</hi> that we may <hi>comprehend with All Saints,</hi> the <hi>Heighths</hi> and <hi>Depths,</hi> the <hi>Breadths</hi> and <hi>Lengths</hi> of what <hi>paſſes Knowledg; That we may be filled with All the Fulneſs</hi> of Him, who can, to perfect <hi>Myſtery, do above All we can ask or think;</hi> and yet to ſhew it no Blind <hi>Chimerick,</hi> or Imaginary thing; <hi>By a Power that Worketh IN us;</hi> To Him be Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in his <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt throughout All Ages,</hi> Amen.</p>
            <p>And in Regard of ſo many <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> Enemies to the Glory of Chriſt and of his Goſpel in this Age, and in the midſt of us; Let us Hereby know to our Conſolation, <hi>It is the very Laſt of the Laſt Time, the Time for God to Work for the Conſuming the Grand Antichriſt,</hi> and all the Leſſer <hi>Antichriſts,</hi> that come out of his <hi>Smoke</hi> with Him.</p>
            <p>The Lord Haſten it in this his very Time; So Joyn, I beſeech you in Supplication with your moſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Humble Affectionate Servant In our Lord Jeſus <hi>T. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:173120:3"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THere hath Lately Appeared in <hi>Print,</hi> A Book Entituled, <hi>Chriſtianity not Myſterious;</hi> And It <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakes to Shew, <hi>There is nothing in the Goſpel, Contrary to Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Above it;</hi> And that no <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine</hi> can be call'd, <hi>A Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Writer</hi> Conceals his <hi>Name,</hi> and I do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to make Enquiry after it; For it is not a <hi>Name,</hi> but <hi>Truth,</hi> and Weight of <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> I would Inſiſt upon; Nor would I, if I could, make Any <hi>Reflexion</hi> upon Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Having All Reaſons in my ſelf for <hi>Humility,</hi> in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard both of Conſciouſneſs of my own Weakneſs, and alſo of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthineſs: I would deal onely with <hi>Things,</hi> and Treat them, as They Require to be Treated; That All may Reſt on the Merit of <hi>True Reaſon,</hi> according to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and not on Sallyes of <hi>Wit,</hi> or <hi>Satyre;</hi> And, that All may be Managed with a <hi>Gravity Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> to the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> and with <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:173120:4"/> of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> as All, who <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> in their <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi> ought to <hi>Speak</hi> and <hi>Write:</hi> I deſire to obſerve the <hi>Apoſtolical Rule,</hi> To give the <hi>Apology</hi> of the <hi>Hope of Chriſtianity</hi> to Thoſe, who Ask for it, <hi>with Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and <hi>Fear;</hi> and, <hi>in Meekneſs to Inſtruct,</hi> If Any <hi>oppoſe Themſelves; If God Peradventure will Give them Repentance to the Acknowledging the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I could Have Heartily wiſh'd, that even the <hi>Writer</hi> of the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> I Deſign to <hi>Review,</hi> had Avoided any thing, that Looks ſo Like <hi>Ridiculing,</hi> and <hi>Expoſing,</hi> as that <hi>Dialogue</hi> between the <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Pariſhioner,</hi> p. <hi>112, &amp;c.</hi> and Left his <hi>Reader</hi> to <hi>Bow</hi> before the <hi>Majeſty of Evidence,</hi> (as He expreſſes it) wherever he Found it: and had Forborn that, as Leaſt <hi>Indecorouſneſſe</hi> of Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, towards Perſons of ſo Great Veneration for their <hi>Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhments</hi> of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> and <hi>Learning;</hi> as alſo their <hi>Early Profeſſion</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> I mean, <hi>The Fathers,</hi> whom He calls, <hi>p. 5. The Herd of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</hi> as if becauſe of Their <hi>Reverence</hi> of the <hi>Myſteries</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> above the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> They were to be Look'd upon as <hi>Irrational,</hi> not to ſay <hi>Worſe:</hi> A Vein of clear, unſullyed Reaſon, eſpecially <hi>Bowing</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>Greater Majeſty,</hi> then what we are too ſuddenly prone to call <hi>Evidence;</hi> I mean the <hi>Authority of God in his Word;</hi> I value above All <hi>Flouriſhes,</hi> tha ſerve the <hi>Reader</hi>'s Diverſion and Airyneſs, rather then his Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Benefit.</p>
            <p>I am glad to find ſo many <hi>Reflexions</hi> on the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> and the <hi>Depths of Sathan,</hi> as I hope they will
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173120:4"/> ſhortly be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſally deem'd, and ſpoken of; I mean That of <hi>Popery,</hi> or <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> ſo Great an Eclipſe upon the Glory of <hi>True Chriſtianity;</hi> becauſe <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> hath ſo often Doomed it to <hi>Impenitency,</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition:</hi> But I cannot but look upon it, as moſt Injurious, to Parallel, in any Degree with it, thoſe Forms of <hi>Sound Doctrine,</hi> ſo often Reproached under the Name of <hi>Syſtems,</hi> or <hi>Syſtematic Theology;</hi> wherein any have taken care to keep, eſpecially Cloſe to Scripture; and thoſe <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Exercitations</hi> upon them are ſuited to Men of <hi>Thought</hi> and <hi>Contemplation,</hi> though not ſo Familiar to Common <hi>Readers,</hi> or <hi>Hearers;</hi> who may yet have thoſe Difficulties Maſticated, and Prepared for them, by more plain <hi>Diſcourſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not yet Plead for Binding Men's <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> to any Words, or <hi>Form</hi> of Words, that do not, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially in <hi>Chriſtian Myſteries,</hi> Keep, as cloſe as may be, not onely to <hi>Scripture-Senſe,</hi> but to <hi>Scripture-Expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> with as little variation as is poſſible; <hi>Comparing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things with Spiritual;</hi> and that they who do this, come neareſt to the Thing, as the <hi>Author</hi> ſpeaks; though with what Deſign, in his Explaining of thoſe Words, <hi>p. 5.</hi> I will not undertake to Judge; Let him therein <hi>Stand</hi> or <hi>Fall to his own Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Things</hi> that give me <hi>Scandal</hi> in the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> are; <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Boldneſs, and Inſolency of the <hi>Frontiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece,</hi> ſo very Contemptuous, and even Contradictory to the Conſtant Language of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> Styling the Goſpel, <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and its Truths, <hi>Myſteries;</hi> whilſt that openly Bears out, <hi>Chriſtianity not Myſterious;</hi> this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173120:5"/> ſavours of <hi>Too mean an Eſteem of the Sacred Stamp, and Superſcription,</hi> and the <hi>Images</hi> it gives of <hi>Things,</hi> and Highly Countenances <hi>Antioſcripturiſm,</hi> which yet the <hi>Writer</hi> would Appear not to have any Favour for.</p>
            <p>I look upon it, as a Juſt Occaſion for a <hi>Chriſtian Zeal</hi> againſt it; That the <hi>Deiſts,</hi> as the <hi>Men of Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Virtuoſo</hi>'s, as they would be Thought, in <hi>Religion,</hi> Take the Pretenſions of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> as Service to Themſelves; Finding ſo much ſettled, in what, They Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count Their own Territory, and Demeſne; <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Free-Will;</hi> And, in the mean time, they Act the Part of <hi>Ananias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira;</hi> They <hi>Keep Back,</hi> or <hi>With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw,</hi> ſome Nobleſt Principles of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> on theſe very Intereſts; To which Secret Service, one cannot, but Suſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, this Diſcourſe is Devoted.</p>
            <p>I cannot but be Troubled; The Obſerving <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> with whom the <hi>Deiſt</hi> is in a Cloſe Allyance, Rejoyces to find his Account in this Suppoſiting a <hi>Dead Child</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Free-will,</hi> as they now go amongſt Men, in the Room of that <hi>Living Spirituous Chriſtianity</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> or at leaſt, That it is <hi>Divided</hi> between a Nominal <hi>Faith,</hi> and a <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> that is indeed <hi>Vain,</hi> and <hi>Science, Falſly ſo Called.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Beaux-Eſprits,</hi> The Men of <hi>Ayr,</hi> and <hi>Wit,</hi> are pleas'd with Meeting the Sacred, and Awful <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> under <hi>Burleſque,</hi> and <hi>Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leny:</hi> which ought to Affect the Sincere Lovers of it with Sadneſs, and Lamenting ſuch a Prophane Temper of the Age.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:173120:5"/>
            <p>I will not Deny, That ſome, not to be Looked upon with ſo Ill an Eye, as the Former, who do not Cloſely In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, nor Penetrate the Scope, and Tendency of ſuch a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, but ſuffer Themſelves to be Impos'd upon by Palli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations, and Pretences, think it Innocent: But even this Deſerves Lamentation, as ſhewing a Soft, and Tame Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendry of the <hi>Faith of the Goſpel,</hi> or a <hi>Gallio</hi>-Like Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that does not Generouſly, and Genuinely Care for theſe Things.</p>
            <p>But All, who more Wiſely and Diſcerningly Conſider ſuch Diſſertations in their Spring, and Iſſue, are Aware, How Deſtructive to, and Subverſive of the Doctrines, Life, and Power, and even of the Profeſſion of the Goſpel, they are.</p>
            <p>On the Whole, therefore I make this Solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, with <hi>Appeal</hi> to Him, who <hi>Searches Hearts,</hi> That I have no other Deſign in this <hi>Anſwer,</hi> but the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God in the <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> and <hi>Glorious Goſpel of his Son;</hi> the Salvation of Souls, That they may <hi>Buy the Truth,</hi> and <hi>not,</hi> on Any Fair Glozes, <hi>Sell it.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I can with All Humble Supplications, and Aſſurance, Commend the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking to the <hi>Divine</hi> Acceptance, in, and through the Mediator, and to His Bleſſing upon it; to the Approbation of Sincere Chriſtians; and to the very Reaſon of the Adverſaries between God, and their own Conſciences.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:173120:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE SCHEME OF THE</hi> TREATISE, Chriſtianity not Myſterious; and of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to it.</head>
            <p>THE Faireſt, and Cleareſt Method for the Attaining Truth in any Debate, is the Plaineſt Laying Down the State of it, or Giving a <hi>Scheme</hi> of what is Agreed on Both Parts; of what is mainly in Difference; and of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Topicks of Argument on each ſide. Theſe therefore I would lay down in one View.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 40, 4, &amp;c.</note>1. There is an Acknowledgment on Both Parts of the Divine Original of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of its Truths; That They are from God: The Advantage of which in Deciding this Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, is; That whatever is regularly Argued from Scripture, and from the very Stream, and Current of it, is to be Own'd, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and Reſted upon as Truth by each Party; and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly Agreeable to Right Reaſon, and Right Reaſon to it.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:173120:6"/>2. There are yet Truths of the Goſpel,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>P.</hi> 40, 41, &amp;c.</note> that could never have been Found out by the Trueſt, or even the Higheſt Created Reaſon, ſeeing they are the <hi>Deeps of God,</hi> and can be known onely by Revelation from Himſelf. The Advantage of this Acknowledgment is; That in Regard of the Original of the Truths of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> whatever of Adorableneſs, and Exciting Profoundeſt Reverence is Imported in <hi>Divine Myſteries,</hi> is for ever due to the Truths of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> as in their Unſearchable Spring, and Origin: And this certainly ought to have Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated a <hi>Zeal without Knowledge,</hi> or Due Conſideration of All, that do but Acknowledge ſo much, in <hi>De-Myſterizing</hi> them (if I may ſo ſpeak) or Laying them Common; This ſhould Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliate to them moſt Humble Veneration, and Love, as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Pledges of the Good-will of the Supreme Being, to ſuch Unworthy Deſpicable Creatures, as we the Children of Men Are, to whom the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is Vouchſafed; and even of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcenſion to Angels, whom Sacred Writing ſhews to have an Intereſt, at leaſt of Beholding with Admiration, and Delight.</p>
            <p>And beſides this, there are Reaſons, as will appear, that what is ſo Originally <hi>Myſtery,</hi> ſhould be always ſo, till ſuch a State of Perfect Comprehenſion, as wherein <hi>All Mystery</hi> ſhall be Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is Acknowledged, That the <hi>Goſpel</hi> is prepared,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sect.</hi> 2, 3. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3d.</note> and even Gloriouſly Accompliſh'd to Inform, and to Illuminate; And that it was Attended with an Undoubted Evidence, and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Power of God in <hi>Miracles,</hi> that might give All Aſſurance, and Satisfaction to the Reaſon, and Mind of Man; That it was, and is from God.</p>
            <p>The Advantage of this Acknowledgment on Both Parts is, That hereby, <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is an Unpaſſable <hi>Gulph Fix'd</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Great <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> and the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> which is a <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs,</hi> as <hi>Darkneſs it Self;</hi> and its <hi>Miracles Lying Wonders,</hi> that is, Wonders of Darkneſs, Like only to the Foul Idolatrous <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and its Fables, as Scripture continually ſhades the one by the othe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Let there therefore be no ſhade of Reproach caſt on the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel Notion, or ſtyle of <hi>myſtery,</hi> from the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> ſeeing the One is ſeparate from the Other, as Light from Darkneſs, or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173120:7"/> as Heaven from Hell, and that by Scripture it ſelf; which, (though it uſes the word <hi>myſtery,</hi> ſo continually, as a <hi>Veſſel of Honour,</hi> and Proper to its own Divine Truths,) hath yet ſet <hi>Antichriſtianiſme,</hi> the Counterfeit of Chriſtianity, under the Title of a <hi>Counter-myſtery</hi> alſo, the <hi>myſtery of iniquity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. It is from hence Agreed on Both parts, that Faith is no Implicit, Sequacious, Blind Aſſent; but a Grace of Greateſt Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Underſtanding, Full of Cleareſt Light, and Percep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Truth, Able to be the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very Preſence, or Solid Argument of <hi>Things not ſeen;</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of <hi>Things Hoped for.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Advantage of this Agreement is, that, if notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this, There ſhall be Found ſome Intimate, and even Eſſential Reaſon, why <hi>myſtery</hi> ſhould be Acknowledged <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery;</hi> and that even becauſe Faith is ſo wiſe, and Intelligent a Grace; It will then come home to the Deciſion of the Main Point, whether <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> be <hi>mysterious</hi> or not, and it will be Decided for it.</p>
            <p n="5">5. We are Both One, That we have not <hi>Adequate Ideas</hi> of the Truths of the Goſpel, nor Behold the Eſſences of the things therein, no more, than we have Adequate Conceptions of the Divine Being, or Attributes; or can Behold the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence: Nor have we ſo much, as Adequate Conceptions of Things in Nature, nor can behold their Eſſences: The Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of this Acknowledgment lies in this, That one Undenyable Senſe of <hi>myſtery,</hi> viz. Some Kind of Concealment, and Reſerve is Found in the Truths of <hi>Christianity;</hi> There are ſuch Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes in them, that we cannot by our ſelves have Proportionate Apprehenſions, nor Adequate <hi>Ideas</hi> of; and yet, that this can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be a ſufficient Reaſon of <hi>myſteryzing</hi> them; But if there may be Reaſons given, why their <hi>Hiddenneſſes</hi> ſhould be called <hi>myſteries,</hi> and the Secrets of Nature not on thoſe Reaſons, ſtyled <hi>myſteries;</hi> Yea, if ſome Reaſon of Great Value may be given, why the Truths of the Goſpel may be called <hi>myſteries</hi> more particularly, then the Divine Being, and Attributes, which yet cannot be <hi>Found out to Perfection;</hi> This Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may be very ſerviceable, and conduce much to the Stating the Principal Point now in hand.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:173120:7"/>6. It muſt of neceſſity be Agreed by All, that have Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for the Goſpel, and the Revelations of it; That there are no Real Contradictions therein; All ſuch are to be Remov'd into the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> with All Things, that would come within the Verge of Religion, and are of a Trivial Nature; or which Falling under a Contradiction in the very Judgment of Senſe, can be likened to a Ball, White and Black together; or a Square that's Round; or a Cane without Two Ends. For all the Truths of Chriſtianity are not only Free from Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but known to be from God, by the Heavenlyneſs, Dignity, Salutarineſs of their Nature, Tendency to the Glory of God, and to the Salvation of Souls.</p>
            <p>But as to ſeeming Contradictions, where the Seemingneſs is the Effect of the Weakneſs, and Darkneſs of our Intellectual Powers, and that are Dimm'd with the Vapors of Corruption, and Steams of Luſt; and where the Objects are Pure, Spiritual, Sublime, and we do not in our Groſſneſs Comprehend them; Herein a more ſtrict Account is to be taken, than the Author hath given.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That to Underſtand the Truths of the Goſpel, ſo as to Receive Them; the Prejudices of a Carnal Mind, and all Luſts are to be Remov'd: Men muſt be Humble, not Proud; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate, not Haſty; Diligent in Search after Truth, not Sloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, or Careleſs; They muſt uſe their Reaſon, and Intellectual Faculties aright: The Advantage of this Acknowledgment on both ſides is, That it lets us into a Great Reaſon, why the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel are to be Allow'd <hi>myſteries;</hi> Becauſe there is a neceſſity of Divine Grace to Enlighten, and Conform the Mind to the Obedience of Faith.</p>
            <p n="7">7. There's a Suppoſition in the Treatiſe of <hi>Supra-Intellectual Truths,</hi> that none can underſtand, except their Perceptions be Communicated to them in an Extraordinary Manner, as by New <hi>Powers</hi> and <hi>Organs.</hi> And, by the ſame Favour theſe Truths are Communicated from One to Another in the Preaching of the Goſpel; Now this Suppoſition, I mean, of <hi>Supra-Intellectual Truths,</hi> and a Supernatural Manner of Communication, at a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and ſo Coldly Suppoſed is That, which I would endeav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our to make good to be the Conſtant, and Uniform Senſe of the New Teſtament; as appears by thoſe Expreſſions <hi>of the Spirit of Wiſdom, and Illumination</hi> (of which the Author himſelf
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173120:8"/> takes notice) <hi>Regeneration,</hi> and <hi>Renovation of the Spirit of the Mind;</hi> And I ſee not what Abſurdity, or Unreaſonableneſs the Author can charge upon it; ſince he owns; There are Men <hi>Taught of God,</hi> and that <hi>God wants not Ability Rightly to Inform them,</hi> as neceſſary to ſuch Communications, <hi>p.</hi> 132.</p>
            <p>That he Himſelf does not ſuppoſe Abſolutely <hi>New Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> or <hi>Organs,</hi> but as by <hi>New Faculties,</hi> or <hi>Organs:</hi> I look upon as a Great Truth of the Goſpel: In this Suppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on therefore, the <hi>Word of God,</hi> which is <hi>ſharp,</hi> as a <hi>Two-Edged-Sword,</hi> ſeems to me, to have met him, as the <hi>Angel of the Lord</hi> did <hi>Balaam in the way,</hi> with a <hi>Drawn Sword,</hi> Warning him, that his Reaſoning is in the Sight of God <hi>Perverſe,</hi> and to be cut in pieces by it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> Herein I am of the ſame Mind with this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Author</hi> of it, as that on which he Builds his Diſcourſe throughout, if it be but Explained Aright; and That Aright (as I ſuppoſe) he will allow, <hi>viz.</hi> For any thing to be <hi>mystery,</hi> is to be <hi>Above our Reaſon,</hi> Acting according to our Innate <hi>Ideas;</hi> thoſe that may be ſuppoſed to be Concreated with us, or that we have a Natural Power to Form, and to Reaſon according to in our preſent ſtate. And whatever is not <hi>Above</hi> theſe <hi>Ideas,</hi> and our Reaſon acting upon them, is not <hi>mystery,</hi> though we have not <hi>Adequate Ideas,</hi> or Perfect Conceptions of Things, or Intuition of their Eſſences.</p>
            <p>Now if Reaſon be taken in this Limited Senſe, there may be, and, as things are, there muſt be <hi>mystery;</hi> But if in a Supreme Abſolute ſenſe, it is certain; As there can be no Truth <hi>Above Divine Reaſon,</hi> ſo there can be no <hi>mystery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Contrary to Reaſon</hi> can only be ſuppoſed of any Truth, as Corrupted <hi>Reaſon</hi> can be called <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Or, as Men will ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately hold their Meaſure of <hi>Reaſon</hi> to be the Standard; ſo that whatever is Higher or Deeper, Longer, or Broader then that Meaſure, or Standard, is not <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but <hi>Contrary</hi> to it: Now either of theſe is ſo Falſly called <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that they have very little Intereſt in the ſtricteſt Conſideration, I confeſs, of <hi>myſtery.</hi> But ſeeing This Corruption of Reaſon, or Adherence to any Short Meaſure, of (though True) <hi>Reaſon</hi> be now a Depravati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Immedicinable, but by the Lifting up of the Mind above it ſelf by a Supernatural Power; The Truths of the Goſpel may
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173120:8"/> too Truely be ſaid to be <hi>Contrary to Reaſon,</hi> and ſo <hi>myſtery;</hi> even as, and more then if they were <hi>Above Reaſon</hi> only.</p>
            <p>The Advantage of this Accord in the Deſcription of <hi>myſtery</hi> is, That hereby a clear, and diſtinct underſtanding of what is principally in Difference, is attained, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Side of the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> it is affirm'd by the Author; There is no Doctrine of Chriſtianity, that can be properly ſtyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>myſtery;</hi> that is; above Reaſon, or contrary to it.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> I Affirm; There are Greateſt Truths of the Goſpel <hi>Above Reaſon,</hi> though not conſider'd, as Corrupt; and many more; Yea, the whole Tenor, and Frame of the Goſpel, as it comprizes the Redemption of Man Fallen, by our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> is Both <hi>above</hi> and <hi>contrary</hi> to it, as Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and ſo <hi>myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And according to the Meaſures of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> ſo are the Powers of <hi>Free-will</hi> to be Arbitrated, and Eſtimated, as ſhall be ſeen, through the Aſſiſtance of God, in the Following Debate.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Topicks,</hi> or Seats of Argument, on which the <hi>Author,</hi> and his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> Rely, are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That when the Truths of the Goſpel are once Revealed, the Mind and Reaſon of Man is able, by its ſelf, to Form <hi>Ideas</hi> of Them, according to <hi>Revelation;</hi> ſo far as is neceſſary to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, however not Adequate; and by Former <hi>Ideas</hi> Implant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to Judge of them, as from God, and according to Truth; Elſe they could be nothing to us any more, than if never Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; nor could we elſe diſtinguiſh them from Falſhood, and Deluſion, ſo proper to the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> And that Man hath a Power of <hi>Free-will</hi> Obedientially to Anſwer the Ends of ſuch Revelations, if not wanting to himſelf; Elſe he could not be juſtly Condemned.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Goſpel is prepared and Addreſſed to the Minds and Wills of Men, according to the former Hypotheſis, or Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and not, as if it were <hi>Myſtery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the Contrary Part, to ſhew, the Goſpel is <hi>Myſterious;</hi> I will endeavour, after the Cloſeſt Purſuits of the Nature of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and of <hi>Revelation,</hi> according to both Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and the Intimate Senſe of Awaken'd Mind.</p>
            <p>From Both theſe therefore Compared, we ſhall Attain the Knowledge; How the very word <hi>Myſtery</hi> came into the uſe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173120:9"/> of the Goſpel, and Adjuſt thereunto the uſe of it in the Impure <hi>Myſteries</hi> of <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm;</hi> and the Common uſe of it in ordinary Concernments; and for what Excellent purpoſes it is to be Zealouſly Contended for in Divine Things, till All <hi>Myſtery be Finiſh'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to Exemplify Goſpel <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Myſtery,</hi> I will do it in Him, who is indeed the Higheſt Exemplar of Both; The Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Logus,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Myſtery;</hi> as he is <hi>Chriſt in us the Hope of Glory.</hi> And hereby we ſhall be led into the Supreme <hi>Myſtery of the Father; The Word; The Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And all along, in Anſwer to this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> I would remove the <hi>Scandals</hi> and Reproaches caſt upon the Truths of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, Aſſerted to be <hi>Myſterious;</hi> and the <hi>Faithful Stewards</hi> of thoſe <hi>Myſteries,</hi> as if they had any <hi>Symboliſm</hi> with <hi>the Myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity;</hi> and ſhew how they differ as Light and Darkneſs.</p>
            <p>In the Laſt Place, Any Objections I can Derive from the <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> that can be ſuppoſed to be made againſt the <hi>Myſteriouſneſs</hi> of Chriſtianity, as it ſhall be made out in the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> ſhall be throughout it, as particularly as may be taken into Juſt, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Conſideration.</p>
            <p>According to this <hi>Scheme</hi> I ſhall, by the Aſſiſtance of God, not only endeavour a Scripture, but a Rational Conviction, that the Doctrines of Chriſtianity are, and muſt needs be in Trueſt Senſe <hi>Myſteries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Conclude therefore this ſhort <hi>Scheme</hi> with Applying that Grave Obſervation to the whole; It is ſaid; <hi>A little Knowledge in Nature makes Men Atheiſts;</hi> But a Deep, and Well-Ballaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Knowledge more ſtrongly Rootes Them in the Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment, and Adoration of the Divine Being; So Superficial Tinctures of <hi>Reaſon</hi> give Men occaſion to Deny the <hi>Myſteriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of Chriſtianity; but the Juſter Preſences of it in the Mind give Fulleſt Aſſurances; It is in All True Senſes <hi>Myſterious,</hi> even the Adorable Myſtery of the Divine Wiſdom and Grace.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:173120:9"/>
            <head>A Diſcourſe of the <hi>Myſteriouſneſs of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity,</hi> in anſwer to a treatiſe, <hi>Chriſtianity not Myſterious.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the cloſe and ſtrict conſideration of Reaſon.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>IN ſpeaking of <hi>Reaſon,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to that Head, The cloſe purſuit after Reaſon.</note> I cannot acquieſce to the ſingling out of that compare, and ballancing of the <hi>Idea</hi>'s of the Mind, and Arguing from them, in finding out Truth, aſſigned in this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, to be a ſufficient Repreſentation of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> but that there ought to be as juſt an Animadverſion, on what the Author does indeed Repreſent; which ought to be taken in, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Mind,</hi> the <hi>Idea</hi>'s <hi>of the Mind,</hi> the Evidences the Mind hath of Notions, or Propoſitions immediately, and as iſſuing in Full Demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And alſo what the Author takes no notice of, <hi>viz.</hi> That Holineſs, Purity, Righteouſneſs, Univerſal Goodneſs and Probity, inſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from <hi>True Reaſon;</hi> That Inward; and <hi>Prophoric,</hi> or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Speech ſo Eſſential to <hi>Reaſon</hi> and that <hi>Energy,</hi> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor, and Power of Imprinting it ſelf upon Rational Beings, ſo immediately reſulting from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> according to the Excellency of the Reaſon, from which it flows: For thus I find Scripture does extend it ſelf, with Relation to what is to be <hi>Diſcourſed</hi> upon,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as <hi>Reaſon, viz. Spirit, Mind, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, the Diſcurſive Mind, Wiſdom, Knowledg, Truth;</hi> The <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> that is the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> the <hi>Knowledg of the Holy,</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the Law
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173120:10"/> Written in the Heart.</hi> The <hi>ſpeaking in the Heart,</hi> or <hi>Communing</hi> with it; The <hi>Tongue of the Wiſe, of the Learned; a might and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, an Authority of Teaching.</hi> But were it not that in one peculiar caſe of greateſt moment (as ſhall be ſet out, but deferr'd till what is more univerſally agreeable, have made the way to it.) I ſhould have no favor for the word <hi>Reaſon,</hi> on a Religious Account; as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word taken from the Pride and Supercile of <hi>Philoſophy,</hi> and not from Scripture; but ſet in oppoſition to the Spirituality of the Goſpel: But ſeeing it hath pleaſed the Spirit of God to ſingle out that word, that all the Great Men of <hi>Reaſon</hi> have expreſſed it by; <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; and to apply it to the Son of God, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as Scripture is, <hi>The Writing;</hi> therein Sanctifying the <hi>Learning of Egypt,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſo Tranſcendent a <hi>Revelation,</hi> and ſo plainly point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the ſenſe of that word, we are to be upon, in ſtyling that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Light of Men,</hi> as <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the General Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation is; and the <hi>Light,</hi> that <hi>Lightneth every man that cometh into the World;</hi> I ſhall generally adhere to it in the following Diſcourſe, and have an eſpecial Regard to it, as it muſt needs be underſtood in this Debate, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or <hi>Reaſoning <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> planted in the Mind, or intellectual Spirit of Man, conſtituting ſuch an Intellectual, Rational Creation; altho in this Fallen Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Man, there are only ſome Reſerves, or ſome Mentions and Ruins of it.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. IT is agreed on both parts, as is acknowledged in the <hi>Scheme</hi> Foregoing; That to be <hi>Above,</hi> or <hi>not above Reaſon,</hi> determines <hi>Myſtery,</hi> or <hi>no Myſtery;</hi> it is moſt neceſſary therefore to Examine, wherein the true nature of <hi>Reaſon</hi> conſiſts, aſcending up to the Supreme and Eternal Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and coming down by the ſeveral Scales, and Degrees of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and in Created <hi>Reaſon</hi> to conſider it as Upright and Entire, and as Fallen and Depraved. To make therefore the Exacteſt enquiry after the Scripture-notion of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> comparing it with the intimate ſenſe of Man-kind (if that ſenſe be duly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected upon) ſhall be the firſt part of my undertaking.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. The very force and weight of the word <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and ſo of <hi>Wiſdom, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Truth;</hi> leads to ſome ſupreme <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>reaſon;</hi> for every name, and pretence to theſe high and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173120:10"/> things, cannot be themſelves; And yet one pretence would be as good as another, and the loudeſt ſound, like the ſtrongeſt ſword, would carry it, were there not ſome Abſolute <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> by which all the various pretenſions are to be Tryed and Determin'd.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. We find among Men, There are various Degrees and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of <hi>Reaſons</hi> and <hi>Wiſdoms</hi> (as we may ſtile them) or of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings;</hi> ſome Higher, and ſome Lower, and we Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Appeal from the Lower, to thoſe we judg Higher; till we come to what we eſteem Higheſt; And if thoſe various <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtandings,</hi> or <hi>Reaſons</hi> are at difference among themſelves; we cannot but acknowledg our ſelves obliged, and we do ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily acquieſce in what we judg the Trueſt, and the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Underſtanding; If we are ſincere in our Search after, and deſire of Truth.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. It is true, this is, becauſe we do; if we do, as Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Beings Ought; Try and Examine, and reduce all to ſome infallible Standard, in which we can acquieſce, and of which we have a Senſe within our ſelves; And He, Or that which we find comes neareſt to that Standard, we moſt defer to, and acquieſce in, and cannot but do ſo; which Argues, we have all a Senſe, or Conſciouſneſs of ſome Abſolute perfect Standard of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> without Agreement with which, what would be Reputed <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> is Inſipience or Folly; what would be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted <hi>Reaſon</hi> is Irrationality, and Abſurdity.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. This Infallible Standard, if we make a curious and home Reflection upon it in our ſelves, we cannot conceive of, as One Abſtracted <hi>Norma,</hi> Rule, or Line of Wiſdom and Reaſon, that doth not know it ſelf, or doth not it ſelf know, that it knows, or underſtands; That doth not Judg ſo, as to know, that it Judges, and That cannot pronounce and declare, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to it ſelf; and know it does ſo; For this were ſuch an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay and Degradation of its excellency, as is moſt intollerable once to ſuppoſe: It muſt be therefore ſome Living, Self-know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Self-intelligent Being, <hi>He, or That which teacheth Man Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, ſhall not It, or He know?</hi> Even All Perfections of Being,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173120:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> Omnipotence, Omnipreſence, Eternity, neceſſarily lead to that Self-knowing, Self-intelligent Living Being, who is all thoſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: And in Univerſal Senſe and Character of Language is the Divine Being, GOD, who is All theſe, and knows he is all theſe; and who is Able, even by the very Perfection of his own Supreme <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> uncontrollably to know, even by that very <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that he is that infallible <hi>wiſdom, Reaſon</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and All who <hi>reaſon</hi> cannot but acknowledg he is ſo; but if there were any ſuch Abſtracted Dead Law, ſtiled <hi>wiſdom</hi> or <hi>reaſon,</hi> God derived the Rule and Meaſure of his Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Actions from, and referr'd them to; that were not Himſelf, and his own Being; He were not then Supreme, but Accountable; and <hi>Apoſtate</hi> Spirits might maintain an Everlaſting and Undecidable Plea againſt God, whether God, or they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves came neareſt to that Rule; but the Glory, Luſtre and Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritude of his Being declare him that Supreme <hi>wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>reaſon,</hi> and the Rule of it; <hi>and Devils Believe and Tremble:</hi> Here then is the Firſt, and moſt Fundamental Notion of <hi>reaſon</hi> or <hi>wiſdom; The Father of Lights, the Father of Spirits, with whom is no varia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor ſhaddow of Turning,</hi> is the Supreme, Abſolute, Infallible <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> and to ſpeak of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and not to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg him Supreme, it is not to <hi>know what we ſpeak, nor affirm.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Excellencies that are to be Attributed to the Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and that we Know cannot but be ſo Attributed.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">§. 1. WIth this Eternal <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> are all <hi>Idea</hi>'s of <hi>Being,</hi> not only Exiſting, but poſſible to Exiſt in the Pure and moſt Exquiſite Truth of each, who gives a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Exiſtence to them, if Infinite Being pleas'd; For Infinite Underſtanding, and Reaſon is the <hi>Origin,</hi> and Exemplar of all
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173120:11"/> 
                  <hi>Ideas,</hi> the Teſt by which they are Tryed, the Beam at which they are weighed; whether Juſt and True, or Counterfeit, Falſe and Light; and the Immenſe Repoſitory from whence they are Deriv'd; Even as Infinite Being is the Source and Fountain of all Being; and thus this Eternal Spirit, Mind and Reaſon Sees by, and in it ſelf, or in <hi>its own Spirit,</hi> its own Infinite Being; and in that Infinite Being all Beings that have been, are, and ever ſhall be; or that if he had pleaſed, might have been, or may be, if he pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es to have them be; according to their ſeveral Natures, Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and the <hi>Ideas</hi> of them. He holds all in himſelf, as the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Being, and according to his own will concerning them All theſe are Held.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. Hence ariſes that great and excellent word, and notion, <hi>Truth;</hi> which is a Correſpondence between Being or Reality, and an Underſtanding, Beholding, and Looking upon it with Judgment; any pretended <hi>Idea's</hi> that are not according to Things, are <hi>Fantoms,</hi> and not <hi>Idea</hi>'s; all other Apprehenſions, Conceptions, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Concluſions, that Created Underſtandings can Form, are nothings, if taken out of the Underſtandings that Formed them; Becauſe Created Underſtandings cannot touch them into Being, as Increated Can; and not only ſo, but Reality and Truth Ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt them, breaks them to nothing, even within the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings that Form'd them, finding things ſo much other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: And which we ought well to conſider; Truth and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity take hold of Thoſe, who had no <hi>Idea</hi>'s of them; and, to their Full Perfection of thoſe, who had only <hi>Inadequate Ideas</hi> of them; as the words of the <hi>Dead Prophets took hold of the Jews,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 1.5.</note> becauſe from God, however Inſenſible of them; of the <hi>Fathers</hi> who heard them, and Believed them not; and of their Children, who were not Born, when they were ſpoken: Now Truth is Infinite, even as the Divine Being and Underſtanding is; and of unexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible multiplicity, as the Divine Diſplayes in the Works of Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Providence are; Deep, unfathomable, and unſearchable, as the <hi>Counſels of his Will are,</hi> till Revealed.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. The Relations, Aſpects upon, mutual Reſpects, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions, Operations between Being, and Being, with their whole ſtate, from the Infinite, Increated Being, to the Higheſt Creat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173120:12"/> Being, and ſo from one to another to the very loweſt of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, are next to be Conſidered; ſome of which are Evident to <hi>Reaſon</hi> by Senſe, ſome by an immediate, intuitive Act of the Mind, or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> now herein, even in theſe mutual Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Reſpects Reſides a ſecond Apprehenſion, or Notion, of what we mean by <hi>Reaſon:</hi> And all the <hi>Reaſon</hi> we have, will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to the Infinite Reaſon to be the infallible Standard of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and Truth herein; For, who, as he can diſcern all the ſtrait, and direct, the Branching out, and Tranſverſe Lines in Created Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings from one to another; and the immediate Influences from himſelf to all Created Beings, in whom all Beings <hi>have their Being;</hi> even as they that <hi>Live,</hi> and <hi>Move,</hi> have their <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in him; for all theſe he holds Originally in Himſelf, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſuſtains, and guides by himſelf; even as he drew them out with ſo admirable <hi>Mathematicks,</hi> that the <hi>Secrets of Wiſdom</hi> herein are <hi>Double</hi> to all that is known to the wiſeſt of Angels, much more to the moſt Curious Human Inveſtigator, of what we call Nature: And from hence ariſes an inexplicable multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of Truth, and ſo of the activity of <hi>Reaſon</hi> concerning it.</p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. The Trains, Deductions, Connexions and Inferences that may be made from one Branch of Being, and the Truths ariſing from it, to another Branch of Being, and the Truths Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing from That, and ſo throughout from the ſeveral Connexions and Enterweavings of one with another, come next under Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and are very particularly to be conſiderd; For from the comparing and ballancing theſe one with another, and the <hi>Idea's</hi> of them one with another flows, what we properly call <hi>Ratioci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,</hi> or Argument of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Now all theſe ſeeth and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by one Intuitive Act of Seeing, the Eternal Underſtanding, or <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and no underſtanding can ſee, or behold them, but in his Light, and according to his Infinite, and Infallible Standard of <hi>Ratiocination;</hi> nor can any Ratiocination upon them be Right, but as they agree with, and are according to this Infinite and Infallible Standard of <hi>Ratiocination;</hi> who holds in himſelf, and continually derives from himſelf thoſe Bonds of Union, and Links of Connexion, things have one with another, on which <hi>Ratiocination</hi> and Argument are founded; and therefore cannot but know, to Infiniy of Certainty, and exactneſs; for what we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173120:12"/> ſee, but one after another, and not with a Juſt Equality, he ſees together, and with a juſt Poize of Each; the want of which preſence of, and regard to all <hi>Idea's,</hi> and the Equipoize of them, was the Ruin of Angels: What truſt then can be to our due Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregating, Compare, and Ballance of <hi>Ideas</hi> one with another; when we either leave out altogether, or do not Righteouſly weigh ſome principal <hi>Idea;</hi> as moſt certainly <hi>befell Adam</hi> in his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception and Fall; and yet herein, even in this <hi>Ratiocination,</hi> or comparing, and librating <hi>Ideas</hi> one with another, The Author of this Treatiſe places <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and it is certainly the <hi>Fort-Royal</hi> of it, altho what went before, and what is to follow, ought to have full conſideration in our Eſtimate of Reaſon.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. In thoſe Accounts of Reaſon before inſiſted upon, we may, and I have endeavour'd to Argue from the little of Reaſon in our ſelves, to the Infinity of Reaſon in the Infinite Reaſon, Wiſdom, Underſtanding, and Truth; But in the Account I would now give of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> I ſhall Argue from the Infinite Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to all Finite Reaſon; That no Reaſon, Wiſdom, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding can be according to Truth ſo, that is not entirely Holy, and Good; and although we want this excellency of <hi>Reaſon</hi> yet we cannot but acknowledg it the excellency of Reaſon, and Aſcribe it to God the beſt of Beings, and Reaſons; That <hi>Reaſon</hi> then is not to be acknowledged <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor worthy Truſt in any Enquiry after Truth, that can betray its Truſt ſo Far, as to Reſign up the Will to any ſin; which according to the Law of Creation, it hath in its Conduct and Power; if there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Underſtanding and Reaſon did not turn away from good by Darkneſs, or not brightning its own Beams, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving an even voluntary Eclipſe upon them, no Evil could be Admitted; For it is indeed certainly true, the Will of a Ration<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Being is one with its Reaſon, and the Reaſon with the Will; when ever one Errs, the other Errs: The wiſeſt of the Fallen Angels is but a <hi>Prince of Darkneſs,</hi> held in <hi>Chains of Darkneſs;</hi> and his Fundamental Wickedneſs is in an Apoſtate, Rebel, Diſloyal Reaſon, Judging that Holineſs, Conformity with, Obedience to the Supreme Being is not Good for him; and ſo it is in us ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Men, and our ſins; and yet becauſe There is Will in this Reaſon, it is under an everlaſting righteous Condemnation: But
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173120:13"/> The Infinite <hi>Reaſon</hi> is Infinite Holineſs and Goodneſs; He <hi>cannot be Tempted of Evil;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 1.13.</note> neither can he <hi>Tempt any one.</hi> If it were not thus, he could not have <hi>made weights for the Winds,</hi> nor <hi>weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Water by Meaſure:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job. 28.23.</note> He could not have <hi>made a Decree for the Rain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3.19.</note> nor a <hi>way for the Lightning of Thunder:</hi> By the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> of Infinite Holineſs <hi>he Founded the Earth;</hi> by an <hi>underſtanding of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Purity he Establiſhed the Heavens;</hi> by a <hi>Knowledg</hi> of Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Freedom from, and diſtance from ſin, the <hi>Depths are Broken up, and the Clouds drop down their Dew;</hi> All the Ordinances of the Creation are ſettled, and ſo kept in Order; There are the ſame <hi>Mathematicks</hi> in one, as in the other; if the Creator could have Err'd in the one, he had in the other alſo; and if he could now ſo Err, the whole <hi>Courſe</hi> of <hi>Nature</hi> would fly in Peices, as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>James</hi> intimates it endanger'd by the Wickedneſs of the <hi>Tongue.</hi> And ſo it is in every Created <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and particularly in Man, if he can ſo miſ-judg, that all Circumſtances laid together, it is not beſt for him to be <hi>Holy, Righteous, Good;</hi> his Reaſon is not to be truſted for any thing, becauſe it is his; Upon his Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, that two and two make Four, is not to be Received: The <hi>Mathematicks</hi> of the whole Creation are Violated in him: For when God <hi>made weights for the Winds,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 28.28. Rom. 2.14.</note> &amp;c. <hi>He ſaid to Man, he fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, as a Being of Reaſon in this; The Fear of the Lord, That is Wiſdom, To depart from Evil, that is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> This is that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; that <hi>In-Written Law</hi> in the Heart of Man. If he does not ſo <hi>Fear,</hi> ſo <hi>Depart, Reaſon,</hi> as it is his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> is worth nothing.<note place="margin">Prov. 3.8.</note> The <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that <hi>Founded the Earth,</hi> &amp;c. Is to <hi>hate Evil;</hi> It <hi>underſtands Righteouſneſs, Judgment,</hi> and <hi>every good Path:</hi> The <hi>Wiſdom</hi> that can entertain Evil, is then of no Value, nor to be truſted in any thing, as it is ſuch a Wiſdom; For the whole of ſuch a <hi>Reaſon</hi> is ſpoiled.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. I know it will be objected; Are not Evil Men great <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſphers, Mathematicians, Politicians</hi> and <hi>States-men;</hi> but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is: The Infinite Reaſon Holds in it ſelf the Truth of all Natural, Prudential, Political Wiſdom, and Underſtanding; and ſo far as it appears by the Evidence of things themſelves, that there is truth, ſo far they are to be received: But the Reaſon tranſpoſed, perverted, diſtorted in the Love of Evil, is in nothing to be confided in for its own ſake; nor is a whole Council of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173120:13"/> Fallen Men to be confided in, in any one Point; becauſe they have Fail'd in ſo Radical a One, as to have ſinn'd; they may not attend to ſome one great Principle, that bears up ſuch, or ſuch a truth; Even as in that Radical One: And though they may Acknowledg and Subſcribe to many Holy Rules, and Live in Obedience to ſome; yet this, as ſhall be further offered, flows from Grace towards ſome, and in others from a Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Judgment of God; who as he holds faſt all Holy Truths in himſelf, ſo Demonſtrates them by others as he pleaſes Variouſly; But it ſtill remains, no ſuch Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Underſtanding, or Reaſon, is to be truſted on its own Account; And all the Truth and Good that is in the World, is to be Aſcribed to other Springs, as we ſhall ſee.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. We know in our ſelves, as we are Beings of Reaſon; Every Intellectual Being hath an Internal Annunciation to it ſelf, and within it ſelf, according to its comprehenſions of Reaſon, that is even Conſubſtantial to it ſelf; and according to which, it De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares it ſelf to other Intellectual Beings, by external Enunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Elocution: And theſe are ſo much <hi>reaſon</hi> that both the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and the outward are expreſſed by Reaſon it ſelf; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: They are the great Diſtinction of Man, the Creature of <hi>reaſon,</hi> from Creatures of no <hi>reaſon;</hi> That Angels have within Them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſuch Internal Notices of their own Comprehenſions, we are moſt aſſured by our own Experience; and that they have Enunciation to other Intellectual Beings of their own order, we cannot doubt, in. Alluſion to which, the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the <hi>Tongue of Angels;</hi> The Excellency of God's Internal and Declarative word, I will Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe on another Head, but to ſpeak of what will not be denyed by any who acknowledg God, and Scripture the word of God; it's this; That if Infinite <hi>reaſon,</hi> Wiſdom and Truth, hath condeſcended to ſpeak, there is no ſuch ſpeech in the whole Creation, as His Word, and the Records of what he hath ſpoken; to contain in it ſelf, and to Reveal <hi>Myſtery;</hi> and no other but his Word can be proper for either. Seeing External Speech is Govern'd by inward Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Power of Enunciation; as the one Excells, ſo does the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; If therefore the underſtanding, and <hi>reaſon</hi> of God be the only Infallible <hi>reaſon,</hi> his Enunciation and Declaration can be only In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible; <hi>Reaſon</hi> in us was his word, and would be ſo, if it were the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173120:14"/> ſame he gave; But it is now fallen: And this Aſſures the Excellency of the Word of God ſpoken or written; There is a Declaration or Voice of God in the Creation, declaring his Infinite Wiſdom, and Underſtanding, to the Intellectual Creation, according to their Firſt Creation; but the word of God declares the Counſels of his Will in Receiving of Fallen,<note place="margin">Pſal. 12.6. Prov. 30.6.</note> and Loſt Man. <hi>Every word of which is pure as Silver tryed in a Furnace of Earth, purified ſeven times;</hi> and whoſoever <hi>dares to add to it,</hi> of his own, as if it were the ſame, or equal, will be <hi>found a Lyar,</hi> that is, a Forger, and Deceiver; or a Reaſon falſly ſo call'd.</p>
               <p n="8">§. 8 Every <hi>rational</hi> Being, or <hi>reaſon,</hi> hath in the motions of <hi>reaſon,</hi> a Force, Might, Spirit of <hi>reaſon,</hi> or preſence of it, active in himſelf, and impreſſive on thoſe to whom he declares himſelf, according to the Degree and Excellency of his <hi>reaſon,</hi> and by which he looks back upon himſelf, and is Conſcious of the <hi>reaſon</hi> that mooves in and from him; and knows that he knows; and this gives Life to the inward Notions, and Notices, or that inward word of <hi>reaſon;</hi> and to the Communications, or Enunciations of <hi>reaſon</hi> to other Intelligent Beings: This aſſures there is in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Being, the infinite <hi>reaſon,</hi> an Infinite Spirit, and Power of Wiſdom, and Underſtanding; of which in its higheſt Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I will further ſpeak by his own Aſſiſtance; But in general Apprehenſion,<note place="margin">Job. 36.22. Job 32 8.</note> 
                  <hi>God Exalteth by his Power, none teacheth like him.</hi> There is a <hi>Spirit in Man,</hi> but the mighty <hi>Breathing of the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty gives him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> a mighty <hi>Energy,</hi> or Spirit from God, the Supreme <hi>reaſon,</hi> and Underſtanding: This we cannot but acknowledg, and Aſcribe to the Supreme Underſtanding: For if we find it in ſuch <hi>Reaſons,</hi> as we are, one towards ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a Communication with ſome peculiar Efficacy, according to the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that does Communicate, or the <hi>Reaſons</hi> that Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate one with another; How much more is it to be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to the Infinite <hi>Reaſon Teaching man Knowledg;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore how can any Gracious Aproaches, by his Spirit, to the Souls of his Servants, Inlightning, and Teaching them be Denyed?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:173120:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of Created <hi>Reaſons,</hi> and their various Orders, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences one to another, as <hi>Beings</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and of their upright and Fallen Eſtate, and the great difference of their <hi>Reaſon</hi> therein.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">§. 1. I Have thus far conſidered the Paramount, and Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Infinite Being, Wiſdom, Truth, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> By thoſe Tracings of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as in Us, not only Finite, but Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Spirits, or Beings of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> that whatever true Lines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are Diſcoverable in us may lead us up to the Infinite, and Infinitely Pure Original; and ſhew us the Immenſeneſs of his Perfections; For it is certain Intellectual Spirits cannot be made ſuch, or continue in any Activity, as ſuch, but that God the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, Intellectual Object, and moſt Intelligible, muſt needs be ſeen by them in his Great Perfection, and Attributes: But I would now conſider Created Intellectual Beings, and ſuch, as we cannot, but by our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Divine, are of a Higher Sphere, and Order, than our ſelves; and Scripture makes known to us, as <hi>Seraphic, Angelic Beings,</hi> and among them <hi>Thrones, Principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Dominions, Powers;</hi> and ſo come down to Human Spirits in Bodies, and obſerve upon theſe, and the various Elevations of them (and All in their State of Integrity, and unfallen) what may Direct us in our main purſuit after <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. All Created Spirits, of what Order ſoever, are Beings, or Spirits Begotten by Creation of the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Spirits in his own Image,</hi> and <hi>Likeneſs;</hi> and ſo are Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectual Spirits, and Beings of <hi>Reaſon</hi> by their very Being, and Deſcent; And in their firſt Creation they bear a Reſemblance of the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> in every one of the foremen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned particulars; as hath been already ſufficiently to the preſent purpoſe Remark'd concerning them: And as there is an Original Begetting, <hi>Breathing,</hi> or Creation at Firſt, ſo there is a continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173120:15"/> ſuſtentation of Intellectual Beings, ſo far, as they are in their <hi>First Eſtate,</hi> or are but preſerved in any Remains of it; and according to the Degrees of their Creation, and Suſtentation, or (as I may call it) their Reſervation in an Intellectual State,<note place="margin">Jude 6.</note> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their <hi>Leaving their Firſt Eſtate, and Forſaking their own Habitation,</hi> They are in Dependence upon their Supreme, a Standard of Wiſdom, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Truth to themſelves, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in themſelves;<note place="margin">Pſal. 36.9.</note> yet ſo that in the Original <hi>Light, Truth, Wiſdom, Reaſon</hi> they ſee this <hi>Light,</hi> and enjoy this Priviledg; that is, they are Intellectually Seeing, Diſcerning Spirits, Beings of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> As the <hi>Spirit of a Man is the Candle of the Lord, a Light ſhining in his Light;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 20.27. Job 35.11.</note> 
                  <hi>who Teacheth Man Knowledg, more than the Beasts of the Field, and the Fowls of the Air:</hi> Thus, as before-ſaid, <hi>There is a Spirit in Man, and the Breath of the Almighty giveth him <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. But yet, it is always to be Remembred; In their very Original Creation, without the conſideration of any after Abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or Diminution; they are but Finite, and cannot ſee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Limits and Bounds of their Creation, either to Find out, or Judg of what is Above, and beyond Them: Any more then the Eye of the Body, becauſe it is a ſeeing Organ, and the <hi>Light of the Body,</hi> can ſee at too great Diſtance, without the help of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcopes;</hi> or when the Object is ſo Great, as not to be meaſur'd by it, but by the Help of <hi>Mathematic</hi> Inſtruments; or ſo Minute, as not to be Diſcern'd, but by the help of <hi>Microſcopes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Of Intellectual Spirits, There are by the very ſupreme Diſpoſe, and Arbitration of the Infinite Underſtanding, and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> various, Spheres, and Orbs Higher, and more Ample; Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and more Narrow; <hi>One Star differs from another Star in Glory:</hi> There are Intelligences <hi>Angelic,</hi> and <hi>Human.</hi> In the <hi>Angelic,</hi> the before obſerv'd <hi>Thrones, Dominions, Principalities, Powers,</hi> which Eminencies Ariſe from different Glories of Underſtanding; and ſo we know, there are different Elevations of Human Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whether by the Immediate Hand of the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> and <hi>Spirits,</hi> or the Diſpoſes of Providence in the Fabric of the Body; or the Opportunities of Education, State and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the World;<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>v. 18.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Separation to Intermeddle with Wiſdom through
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173120:15"/> earneſt Deſire;</hi> But no Intellectual Created Spirit can, by vertue of its being Intellectual, Tranſcend its own Sphere. The higheſt Created Spirit cannot Approach within any diſtance of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>created; or be ſuppoſed Infinite in its Reaſon, becauſe a Spirit; For God is, <hi>The only Wiſe, and his <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is alone Infinite.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 147.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> That therefore which is clearly known, and within the compaſs of the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Intellectual Beings of a <hi>Firſt Magnitude,</hi> may be above the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of thoſe <hi>Below Them,</hi> and ſo ſucceſſively and Subalternately, till we come to the Loweſt; but to the longhty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Seraphic</hi> Underſtanding, There are in the Divine Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, Truths, and Deeps of Counſels, that are above the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it; ſo that it can be only ſaid of the <hi>Infinite <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> There is nothing <hi>above Reaſon,</hi> that is, above it ſelf, nor contrary to it, that is <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. But how much more muſt many, and thoſe very great Truths of God be above <hi>Reaſon</hi> to Fallen Loſt Man, ſo depreſſed and abaſed by ſin, that he cannot lift up himſelf, but with great Difficulty in any Act of Underſtanding? and whoſe <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as hath been before more fully Argued, can be of no Reputation; becauſe it can, upon all circumſtances conſider'd, give its ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate Vote, or Dictate for Sin: For now the Intellectual Spirit being under an Averſion from the <hi>Father of Lights,</hi> diſtorted by Luſt, and Love of Evil, is eaſy of Acceſs to the <hi>Father of Lyes,</hi> Blinding and Bemiſting it, to whom it is now Turn'd; How then can it form <hi>Idea's</hi> of Divine Things? Behold the Proportions, and true Reſpects of Things one to another? Judg of Good and Evil, of true Pleaſure, or Grief, and Pain, in a Moral Senſe, of Happineſs or Miſery? How can it make true Inferences, or Concluſions? Riſe up to the Holineſs of the Law of God, or receive his Manifeſtations of himſelf, or ſubmit to the <hi>Energies</hi> of his Grace it ſelf, ſo corrupted? What was not <hi>Above</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Corrupted, is now become <hi>Above</hi> it; How much more Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural Revelations! Nay, They are contrary to <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſo Corrupted, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> Corrupted to theſe Truths of God; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which it moves in Array, as Black Clouds and Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pors againſt the Sun, and its Light: So do Intellectual Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (Angelic become Diabolic) <hi>Rulers of the Darkneſs of this
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173120:16"/> World,</hi> and Degenerate Human Spirits againſt the Light, and Truths of God, and of his Word.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. If it be ſaid, The Luſts of Men are not <hi>Reaſon;</hi> It is True; but as the Enquiry is in <hi>Job; Where is wiſdom to be found, and where is the Place of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> viz. in its Purity? <hi>ſeeing it is hid from the Eyes of all Living: Even as it is kept cloſe from the Fowles of the Air: Death and Deſtruction have heard the Fame of it with their Ears: God alone underſtandeth the way thereof:</hi> And if Man hath loſt, what God ſaid to Him concerning it, (and is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Conviction, how much it is Loſt) by Creation; <hi>The Fear of the Lord, that is Wiſdom, and to depart from Evil, is <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> Wherein can his <hi>Reaſon</hi> be Now Accounted of? All muſt be Reſolv'd, into what <hi>Solomon only found, Counting Men one by one; God made Man upright;</hi> He made him him an entire <hi>Reaſon;</hi> but he hath <hi>ſought out many Inventions,</hi> carrying a ſhew of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but <hi>Reaſon</hi> is loſt: A Diſtorted <hi>Reaſon</hi> is not to be confided in: Such is that of All men; <hi>In one Man</hi> only, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Second</hi> Adam, <hi>Reaſon</hi> is found, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.27.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. If it be further ſaid, Shall we Allow no <hi>Reaſon,</hi> nor Truth in the World? Is It no Teſt to Try True, and Falſe, Good and Evil by? And if it be, why may not <hi>Reaſon</hi> be Truſted in every thing? And if it be not, How ſhall we ſecure our ſelves from being impoſed upon? The Anſwer ſhall be given in its proper place, unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Head of Revelation to each of theſe Enquiries by way of Anſwer to them as Objections.</p>
               <p n="8">§. 8. But ſeeing this Treatiſe makes acknowledgment of Scripture by ſo many References to it, I think to ſum up this head, <hi>viz.</hi> The Purſuit after the true Notion of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> according to Scripture, and our Inward Senſe, and Experience, by giving the general Senſe of Scripture upon the preſent State of Human <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> Wiſdom, and Underſtanding in our Fallen Condition; that we may ſee how far, in the Judgment of That, it can be thought of Value to Decide Truth by, <hi>viz.</hi> This <hi>Above,</hi> or contrary to <hi>Reaſon;</hi> that is, to Human <hi>Reaſon;</hi> yea, we might Aſcend higher, even to higheſt Created <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Unfallen Angels; in <hi>whom God puts no Truſt,</hi> tho his <hi>Servants Fulfilling his
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173120:16"/> Will,</hi> and the <hi>Ministers</hi> of his <hi>Pleaſure, but charges with Folly,</hi> comparing them with his own <hi>Holyneſs,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> which is <hi>Infinite;</hi> and therefore they cover not only their <hi>Feet,</hi> but their <hi>Faces,</hi> their higheſt Perfections before him: For theſe <hi>Stars are not pure in his ſight;</hi> but as to the preſent purpoſe of Human <hi>Reaſon, Zophar,</hi> ſo near the beginning of the VVorld, takes notice;<note place="margin">Job 11.12.</note> 
                  <hi>That vain man would be wiſe;</hi> He Aſpires to the Reputation of being ſo; tho <hi>he be Born like the wild Aſs Colt,</hi> the moſt Undiſciplinable of all Animals, ſo ſilly and ſo wild, and yet the Emblem of Human VViſdom: Notwithſtanding this, every Age hath Riſen up in this preſumption upon their own <hi>Reaſon;</hi> This is that <hi>Gnoſticiſm</hi> of every Age: The Apoſtle ſays, <hi>we know that we all have Knowledg?</hi> that is, we take upon us to have ſo;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.2.</note> But he adds, <hi>If any man think he knows any thing, he knows nothing yet, as he ought to Know;</hi> and therefore he prefers the <hi>Love of God,</hi> and being <hi>known of him</hi> to our <hi>Airy Knowledge</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 4.2.</note> He looks upon them, as Men of no <hi>Topicks?</hi> that is, of no <hi>Reaſon,</hi> who <hi>have not Faith;</hi> who are not inſtructed of God by his Spirit in his Word: Yet we Dwarfs of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> of a Span long, and Hand Breadth, dare to meaſure <hi>Reaſons</hi> with the <hi>Almighty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note> 
                  <hi>vainly pufft up in our minds,</hi> which are but <hi>Carnal,</hi> while we think them ſo ſublime as to meaſure Divine Things; <hi>In the wiſdom of God, the World by wiſdom knew not God: The Lord knoweth the Thoughts of the wiſe,</hi> that <hi>they are vain,</hi> even the Diſcurſive <hi>reaſonings of the wiſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.20, 21. c. 3.18, 19, 20.</note> 
                  <hi>The wiſdom of this world is Fooliſhneſs with God.</hi> Let a man <hi>become a Fool, that he may be wiſe:</hi> With innumerable ſuch Scriptures that would put an humble Chriſtian quite out of conceit with his own <hi>reaſon,</hi> and make him rather cry out with <hi>Solomon, All this have I proved by wiſdom, I ſaid, I will be wiſe, but it was far from me: That which is far off and exceeding Deep, who can find it out?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7.23. Prov. 30.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Surely I am more bruitiſh than any man; I have not the underſtanding of man; viz.</hi> In his firſt Creation. <hi>I neither learned wiſdom, nor know the knowledg of the Holy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 12.3.</note> The Great Wiſdom is not to be wiſe <hi>above what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten;</hi> but to be <hi>wiſe to Sobriety:</hi> So little in all this, and much more, that might be Collected of the ſame Senſe, doth Scripture ſet by <hi>above,</hi> or <hi>contrary</hi> to Human <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as now current among Men: For what the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Man condemns as the <hi>Fooliſhneſs</hi> of God, or <hi>Fooliſhneſs in Divine Things,</hi> that do not commend themſelves
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173120:17"/> to <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or the Wiſdom of Men, is yet <hi>wiſer</hi> than that Imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> of Men.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the Second Head propoſed in this Diſcourſe, An En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry after the Nature of <hi>Revelation,</hi> with an Anſwer upon it to Former Objections.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THere needs no Introduction concerning the word, or ſenſe of the word <hi>Revelation;</hi> For it plainly ſignifies the unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering and making plain, viſible, and open, what was before Covered, Vailed, Hidden, and Concealed: And this is the <hi>Apocalypſis</hi> every where ſpoken of in Scripture from God and his Spirit; and herein the Diſcourſe, <hi>Chriſtianity not Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> agrees, and acknowledges <hi>Myſteries</hi> before <hi>Revelation,</hi> as being of the <hi>Deeps of God,</hi> which <hi>no Man</hi> can know, ſeeing not the <hi>Deeps of a man:</hi> But it is ſuppoſed that <hi>Revelation</hi> is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended to Reaſon, and is no more than Information, or Teſtimony from any other Hand; the certitude only of Divine Excells; For in Human Information <hi>Reaſon</hi> Judges of the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibility, and if it finds cauſe, diſallow the Veracity of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, and rejects the Things; but in Divine Information, it allows the Teſtimony; but if it cannot receive the things as cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible in ſuch an appearance, <hi>Reaſon</hi> changes them by Interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, into other appearances, wherein it can allow them; altho it be never ſo plain by compare of Scripture, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> guided by it, Scripture intends what <hi>Reaſon</hi> Rejects; but I ſhall endeavour to make plain by Scripture, and true <hi>Reaſon,</hi> according to it, and the conſent of Experience; that this is a wholly miſtaken Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient, as I go on thus to Remonſtrate.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. <hi>REvelation</hi> is a Manifeſtation of God to his Intellectual Creatures from the Secret of his own <hi>Purpoſe,</hi> and the <hi>Deeps</hi> of his <hi>Counſel</hi> towards them, or any of them, above what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173120:17"/> was made known to them, or might be found out by them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their Firſt Creation, or Eſtabliſhment; but they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from an Holy, Wiſe, and Infinitely Gracious Being, They are and cannot but be in every one of theſe Regards like to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and as they are ſuper-induced to Creation, they are of Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and higher Grace; for what-ever was neceſſary to the Firſt Creation, was given, and made known by the Infinitely wiſe and good Creator; who yet being Infinite, and Infinitely Free, had more to give than he gave at firſt, but was not obliged to Give all at once: Now theſe things could not be known but by <hi>Revelation, For what man knows the things of a man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.11.</note> 
                  <hi>but the Spirit of a man, that is within him: Even ſo the things of God knoweth no man, but the Spirit of God:</hi> The Goſpel on this Account is ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten Stiled, <hi>The Myſtery hid in God, kept ſecret ſince the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; hidden Wiſdom, the wiſdom of God in a miſtery;</hi> Angels there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Principalities</hi> and <hi>Powers</hi> could not by their Higher Light, than that of the human Creation, find it out; <hi>but learn it by the Church:</hi> This is indeed Agreed, but yet ought to be ſet in its clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and fulleſt Light.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. The Intellectual Eye was in Creation enabled to ſee, and behold only the Objects proper to ſuch a Creation, as it was Created; even as the <hi>Beasts of the Field,</hi> and <hi>Fowls of the Heavens</hi> have no higher a Light, than that of ſenſe, as proper to their Creation: So have the Higher Creations, each in their Claſſe, a Light Proportionable to ſuch, or ſuch an Elevation of Creation; For elſe ſuch higher Light muſt be ſuppoſed to have lain Superfluous, or might have <hi>known the mind of the Lord,</hi> and been his <hi>Counſeller</hi> before Revelation, or could, at leaſt, have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately comprehended the ſecret Counſels of God, whenever <hi>Revealed;</hi> But <hi>Angels Learn,</hi> and <hi>Deſire</hi> to <hi>Look</hi> into them Further and Further; and undoubtedly partake of that grand Priviledg of the <hi>Church, the Spirit of Revelation to Enable them;</hi> That which puts the matter out of all doubt, is; that the Apoſtle joyns, and ſo Scripture throughout, the <hi>Spirit of God Given,</hi> and <hi>Receiv'd;</hi> that we might know and Diſcern: Now the Spirit is not an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, but an inward Revealer, and Elevator of the Spirit of a Man; as <hi>Elihu</hi> ſpeaks in <hi>Job,</hi> God <hi>Exalts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Job 32.26.</note> 
                  <hi>lifts up by his Power</hi> the Spirit of his Creatures whom he <hi>Teaches; who,</hi> therefore
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173120:18"/> 
                  <hi>Teaches,</hi> like him: The Spirituality of this Higher New Creation, is as much above <hi>Rationality,</hi> as <hi>Rationality</hi> above <hi>Senſe;</hi> herein therefore differs Divine <hi>Teaching</hi> from all Created <hi>Teaching:</hi> If any of the <hi>Angels</hi> be ſuppoſed, the Higher to <hi>Reveal</hi> to the Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, or to men, what they Know by the much Larger Sphere of their Creation, and what is <hi>Miſtery</hi> to thoſe, that are of a more confined compaſs, and below them; they may Congregate, and ſtir up by Reaſoning, and Inſtruction all the Light, ſuch had before, and extend it as far as it can be extended under the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutemency of the Eternal Light, and <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſuſtaining and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, both the higher and lower Intellects; but they can give no Inward Supernatural Light, when what they find is not ſufficient; That is the Glory of the <hi>Father of Glory,</hi> and <hi>of Lights;</hi> The Exalting Spirits by his Spirit is his Prerogative alone; and what hath been ſaid of Light, may be much more affirmed of Grace, Love, Holy Conformity of the whole Spirit to <hi>Revealed</hi> Truth; That is from the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>all Grace by his Spirit;</hi> ſo that the Author of the Treatiſe <hi>Saw,</hi> and yet would not, or did not <hi>ſee in ſeeing</hi> the Renewing the Faculties by the Spirit of God, Given now; and of the very Organs in the <hi>Spiritual Body,</hi> a Body fitted by the <hi>Quickning Spirit,</hi> at the Reſurrection, and the <hi>Finiſhing All Myſtery,</hi> to ſee things above <hi>Reaſon</hi> (as was before obſerv'd in the Scheme) which Scripture every where Teaches, is done by the Spirit of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Revelation.</hi> And yet the Dignity of the Firſt Creation is herein ſtill affirm'd, That <hi>the Father of Spirits</hi> hath given the Immortal Spirit of Man <hi>in his own Image;</hi> ſo that it is capable of the <hi>Inhabitation</hi> of his own <hi>Spirit,</hi> as an Higher Spirit in it; and hath alſo Engrafted, and notwithſtanding, ſin Reſerved, ſuch Principles of Truth, that are of Great Service, and Uſe in the Renovation, as ſhall be more ſhewn.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. If now the Light of Creation be ſo unable, without an higher Illumination, and Grace; tho conſidered without any Loſs, or Abatement of it ſelf; not only to find out, but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Revelation;</hi> much leſs can it be a Standard to it, when it is but a Partial Light, and not Adequate to Truths above its Sphere; what ſhall we think then of a Broken, Shatter'd, Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack'd <hi>Reaſon,</hi> whoſe <hi>Light</hi> is <hi>Darken'd in its very Heavens:</hi> For that it is ſo, is Evident, not only by all the Difficulties of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173120:18"/> attaining <hi>Wiſdom, a far off</hi> and <hi>Exceeding Deep</hi> in all kind of Knowledg; but the Imperfections, many Miſtakes, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, not born up by Truth; ſo that when we ſay, <hi>we will be wiſe, it is far from us.</hi> All theſe plainly ſhew a Degraded Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. But that which I look upon, as the moſt Pungent Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration to every Mans Conſcience, is, that however we may be, or are convinc'd of <hi>Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, Soberneſs;</hi> yet <hi>Reaſon</hi> is not Able to give its laſt Poſitive, Peremptory, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſive Dictate; That theſe are beſt for us in all our Actions: This ſhews ſome <hi>Vertical</hi> Point in all Probity, <hi>Reaſon</hi> in this State it is now in, does not ſee: Now this is the principal Point of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> and of <hi>Reaſon;</hi> And it was given in Creation, when to Man, he ſaid equally with making <hi>weights for the Wind, The Fear of the Lord, That is wiſdom;</hi> and not only to know, we ought to do it, but Actually, to <hi>Depart from Evil,</hi> is <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> And Any <hi>Reaſon</hi> that does it not, is <hi>Laeſum Principi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> a Reaſon Broken, and out of Joint; For if it were not, it would Operate true to the very utmoſt Point of All Goodneſs; even as all other Laws of Creation are obſerv'd, ſo had that Law firſt Given of the <hi>Fear of the Lord,</hi> and <hi>Departure from Evil in Man.</hi> The Reaſon of Man is now like the Failure of an Inſtrument, or an Engine of the <hi>Virtuoſoes</hi> in <hi>Experimental Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy,</hi> All ſeems to be ſet Fair, and True, and Right; But it miſſes in the laſt point of Effect: And therefore notwithſtanding all Probabilties, and handſome Appearances, it is not to be truſted Thus the preſent <hi>Reaſon</hi> of Man Judges for Piety, Juſtice, and: Temperance, and ſo ſeems Right for its Purpoſe, and End, but it miſcarries in the Doing; It is not Bleſſed in the Deed, and ſo is not for its own ſake in any thing, to be Truſted: The Reaſon of the Firſt Man did not thus <hi>ſtart aſide as a broken Bow</hi> juſt at the Mark, before his Sin and Fall: If you ſay then, How did <hi>Sin Enter?</hi> The Anſwer is plain; <hi>Adam</hi> Luxated, and ſtrain'd his <hi>Reaſon</hi> in Judging by it, of what was above it; matter of <hi>Revelation;</hi> of becoming <hi>Like God</hi> more than he was by Creation, not Acquieſcing by Faith in the Will of and Grace of the Creator, and obedience to his Command in <hi>not Eating;</hi> and ſo was <hi>Deceived,</hi> and Diſobey'd, and Ruin'd Himſelf and His Poſterity by the Righteous Judgment of the All-mighty, whoſe <hi>ways are paſt finding out by Reaſon;</hi> for they are above it.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173120:19"/> And yet by Truſting in our Bankrupt Reaſon, we daily more Entangle our Selves. Can we think the Fallen <hi>Adam</hi> was to be Truſted, for not the Finding out (that may be Allowed in the Negative) but for the Judging of, or Receiving a Revelation of the way of his Recovery by a <hi>Reaſon</hi> that had ſo fouly miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carryed in Reaching beyond it ſelf: And how much leſs is ours to be confided in, as to what is above it, which does ſo daily fall ſhort of what was at firſt placed in a Juſt Level to that <hi>Reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. The grand <hi>Revelation</hi> of God in his Word, and Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel is the Recovery of Loſt Man by his own <hi>Begotten Son;</hi> who <hi>came from Heaven</hi> into that very Loſt Nature, and Redeemed from Death, Hell, the Curſe, the Wrath, and Juſtice of God by his own Death, and by the Sacrifice of Himſelf, and by His Mediation, and Interceſſion <hi>at the Right Hand of God;</hi> and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing at laſt in the Reſurrection of the Dead Bodies of his Saints, and the Glorification of the whole Man, is <hi>become the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Eternal Salvation to All that Obey Him,</hi> Heb. 5.9. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Fall in All thoſe Truths of the Goſpel, attendant here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, and that concenter with them: Even the <hi>Godlineſs, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Soberneſs,</hi> that the True <hi>Reaſon</hi> hath Loſt, are here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by Reſtor'd, and Brought to Light in a much Higher Luſtre, and Spirituality, with a greater Efficacy, and more Indefeizable certainty, That they ſhall not be Loſt, when the Spirits of thoſe Redeemed by Chriſt are Redintegrated in them.</p>
               <p n="9">§. 9. This is now ſuch a <hi>New Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> of Things, that the Reaſon of Man, if it were whole, and entire, as in the Firſt Creation, could not, by it ſelf Judg of, nor Try in its own Beams, the Supreme Excellencies and Splendors of, but would be Oppreſſed with the Glory, and Dazl'd with the Bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefs; however in ſome, as it were <hi>Back-Parts,</hi> it would ſee a Divinity in them; As to thoſe Glories, that may be ſtiled the <hi>Face</hi> of them, it muſt, even as <hi>Angels,</hi> ſubmit it ſelf to the Paramount and Infinite Reaſon, and <hi>ſhut</hi> its <hi>Mouth</hi> at, as at that, which <hi>Had not not been Told</hi> it, and that <hi>It had not Heard,</hi> in firſt Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation; How much leſs then can the Decayed <hi>Reaſon,</hi> thoſe Poor Relicks, Fragments, and Broken Peices of <hi>Reaſon</hi> judg of them! But through that Sin and Impurity, that hath United it ſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173120:19"/> the more it endeavours to Rally, and Re-unite it ſelf (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of that Corruption wherewith it is ſo Tainted, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed, that even the <hi>Mind</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelieving</hi> are <hi>Defiled</hi>) Not only the greater Ignorance, and want of Skill, but the greater Enmity and Hatred to ſuch a Superior Light, ſtirr'd up, as well as blinded by <hi>Sathan,</hi> It Diſcovers and Detects it ſelf of; And all Directions, Advices, or Commands to Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate it ſelf from that Corruption, are but Preſcribings to the <hi>Blackamore to change his Skin, and the Leopard his Spots.</hi> For this Corrupted <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelf Teaches ſo (and can do no otherwiſe) to Refuſe Divine Truth.<note place="margin">Jerem. 13.23.</note> Hence have ſprung all thoſe Bold and Daring Efforts of pretended ſhrewdneſs of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Inſolencies of it in Scorn and Raylery againſt the Purity of the Doctrine of Chriſt; That Arch-Fallen <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the Devil, Turnes himſelf into all ſhapes, ſometimes as a ſevere Rationaliſt, ſometimes as a <hi>Sarcaſtic</hi> Scoffer, and ſometimes is <hi>Transform'd into an Angel of Light,</hi> and as a Zelot for the Honour of Chriſtianity; and therefore it is no wonder,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> if his Miniſters are Transform'd ſo alſo, and even, <hi>as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs:</hi> And all theſe very Shapes hath The Treatiſe, we have to do with, put on.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. It will be ſaid, If <hi>Reaſon</hi> be not in a Capacity to Receive <hi>Revelation,</hi> what ſhall Receive it? Is it to be ſwallowed in Ignorance, and Blind Obedience, or by an Implicit Faith? the Anſwer is: The Infinitely, <hi>Only Wiſe God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.27.</note> (as the Apoſtle Adores him upon the very Account of the <hi>Goſpel, the Myſtery, kept hid, and Revealed after for the Obediente of Faith) hath prepared a New Creation, a Regeneration, a Renovation of the Spirit of the Mind, viz.</hi> Faith, a New Underſtanding, and Light; a Grace of great <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and Intelligence; and were it not for Confounding it with the Exploded Fallen <hi>Reaſon;</hi> as men are ſo inclin'd to do, who are ſo <hi>Deſirous</hi> to be <hi>Teachers</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but not <hi>Rationally,</hi> as the <hi>Jews</hi> were of the <hi>Law,</hi> but not <hi>Lawfully;</hi> not <hi>Knowing what they ſay,</hi> nor whereof <hi>they affirm;</hi> It might be call'd,<note place="margin">1 Tim. 17.8.</note> a New <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> that ſees in, and by, and is wholly guided by <hi>Revelation,</hi> in, and from the word of God, <hi>Dwelling richly in it,</hi> in <hi>All Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Spiritual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> And in this Light it <hi>Proves</hi> and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amines <hi>all Things, and holds faſt that which is good;</hi> And that which is Above All, In this <hi>New Creation,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> the Light
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:173120:20"/> of it; The great Redeemer by his Spirit, Unites himſelf to the <hi>Renewed Spirit,</hi> and <hi>Dwells</hi> in it; which is a Spirit of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17. 1 Cor. 2.12.</note> and ſo <hi>Reveals the Deeps of God, that we might know the Myſteries of the Kingdom of God, and the Things, that are freely given us of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. If it be further Demanded, Is the Firſt Creation, and the Reaſon of it wholly Antiquated, and Removed in the <hi>New Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> The Anſwer is, All the unchangeable and unmovable Parts of it are comprehended, and taken into the <hi>New Creation,</hi> and much Exalted; And even, as to men Unrenewed, and before <hi>Renovation,</hi> The Great Redeemer hath laid hold upon, and made a Reſerve of ſome great Principles of Truth, and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> or Re-imprinted them in the Minds of Men in General; and the <hi>Law is Written in the Heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 2.14.15</note> even of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> for many Great and Wiſe Ends of the Government of the World; And that Theſe may give Teſtimony to the Holineſs, Purity, Divineſs and Wiſdom of the Truths of <hi>Revelation;</hi> They are a kind of Rude Draught, or Indentings, which the New Creation takes hold of in the Minds of Men, that they may know by them; The Light of the Goſpel is from Heaven, and of God: And on the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of this, They are Righteouſly <hi>Condemn'd,</hi> who do not Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Truths of it, ſo far, as theſe Impreſſions of Natural Light Lead; and it is certain here is the Condemnation of men, that <hi>They have not Believed in the Name of the Son of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joho 3.18.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they loved Darkneſs, rather than Light;</hi> and that becauſe, <hi>Their Deeds are Evil:</hi> And on this Account alſo, even in Devils, and Loſt Spitits, thoſe Principles of ſo Great Light given in the firſt Creation are Preſerv'd by God in Higheſt Actuation, that do, what they can, They may Glorify His Juſtice in their Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; Thus is his <hi>way in the Sea, and his Path in the great Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and <hi>his Foot-ſteps cannot be Traced as yet,</hi> or in the way of his preſent Government of the World; <hi>He, who is Light,</hi> and in <hi>whom is no Darkneſs</hi> at All, Cauſes Light to prevail to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, where it hath not, and does not prevail to Conformity, and Obedience to it; But in the <hi>New Creation; Behold, all things become New.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17.</note> There is Inward, Supernatural Illumination, and the Power of Grace, and Holineſs Conforming the whole Intellectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Spirit to it; and Comprizing alſo within it ſelf the Firſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:173120:20"/> ſo that it is known to be that Firſt Illumination, that <hi>Revelation</hi> hath yet taken wholly into it ſelf, that there may be no miſ-judging by a Partial Light, and yet the Teſtimony of that Light preſerved, Steered, but Exalted Far, above it ſelf.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. It may be largely Remonſtrated upon, how great Affiance there is due to the Light, and conduct of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of States, of Families, of Human Affairs; in all Sciences and Arts, <hi>Aſtronomy, Phyſick, Mathematicks, Muſick, Agriculture, Architecture, Navigation, Manufacture;</hi> and how certain, and evident the concluſions, that are made according to it are; and what Truſt therefore may be given to it in Religion? But on the other ſide, we ought to conſider, How much Darkneſs and Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance there is; How difficult and ſlow the Attainments of Knowledg are; How many things yet unknown; How many Errors, and Miſtakes, hardly found out, and more hardly Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected; what great Differences, and Diſagreements of Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in moſt things pretended to be known; And we ſhall have great cauſe to Reſolve all the Honour and Glory, we think ſo due to Human <hi>Reaſon</hi> into the Glory and Praiſe of the Infinite <hi>Reaſon, Wiſdom, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Truth</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs;</hi> who holds All Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Truths together in his own Underſtanding, even as in his own Uochangeable, and Immenſe Being; elſe all had been ſoon Diſſolved; and who, for his own Glory, and Government of the whole Creation, gives ſuch, and ſuch Degrees of Aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to the Underſtanding of Man in ſo many Things; and yet Humbles it under ſo many, and ſo great Failures; That it may not preſume upon it ſelf, eſpecially in things relating to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, being convinced of its own ſhortneſs, in what, it is more eaſily ſenſible of: Of all which Thoſe laſt Chapters of God's Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulation with <hi>Job,</hi> are ſo great an Admonition, I need enlarge no further upon it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>S.</hi> 8. It may, in the laſt place be urg'd, what ſecurity have we againſt all the Impoſtures of <hi>Paganiſm, Antichristianiſm, Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metiſm,</hi> and other Portentous, and Monſtrous Opinions, that may be impoſed upon us under the Sacred Name of <hi>Revelation,</hi> and things <hi>above Reaſon;</hi> and not to be Examined by it? If we have not ſuch a Faithful Teſt, as our own <hi>Reaſan</hi> always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:173120:21"/> to us, and that may guide us out of All theſe Mazes and <hi>Labirinths;</hi> But on the other ſide, It is a very great diſreputation to Human Reaſon, that ſo great Parts of Mankind have been Involved in theſe ſo Horrible Deluſions; and that it hath not guided them betterr; and it leads us to the Profoundeſt Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation under the Senſe of the Righteous Judgment of God upon his Intellectual, Lower Creation, fallen from him by Sin, and ſo abuſed and deceived by That higher, <hi>Angelis Apoſtate</hi> Nature, called <hi>Sathan;</hi> and to earneſt Supplication to him through the Redeemer, That, that Bleſſed Time may come quickly, when the <hi>Knowledg of the Glory of the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay. 11. Hab. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Knowledg of the Lord ſhall fill the Earth, as the waters cover the Sea;</hi> and alſo to Adore him, that we have the Light of his Goſpel a much ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Guide, than our own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as it is now; and a much higher Light, than it was before its ſo great debaſement by Sin; in which we find all the true, pure <hi>Reaſon</hi> that we have Loſt, or that we have any Sentiments, Foot-ſteps, or Remains of in us; or that we can find in our ſelves; that may aſſure us, as far as <hi>Reaſon</hi> can aſſure us, It is of God; and in which, the things that are moſt above our <hi>Reaſon</hi> ſhed yet ſuch Beams of Light upon our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and trueſt <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as Aſſures; They are from the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and not of <hi>Lyes,</hi> awakening and Enlightning <hi>Reaſon,</hi> while it raiſes us far above our <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and wherein we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, that Higheſt, moſt Aſſuring, <hi>Sealing, Holy</hi> and <hi>Comforting Spirit,</hi> the <hi>Spirit of God;</hi> the only <hi>Paraclet,</hi> the Advocate of truth within us, promiſed to us; for which we ſhould al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Pray with an <hi>Importunity</hi> that will not be <hi>aſhamed,</hi> that it may be given given to us; and in which it is much better to <hi>Trust,</hi> with <hi>all our Hearts,</hi> then to <hi>Lean to our own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding;</hi> Tho they were as the Underſtandings of Angels,<note place="margin">Luke 1.5. Prov. 3.5.</note> in which ſo great a Number of them truſting, and not in that Higher <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> and <hi>Spirit</hi> Fell, and are in <hi>Chains</hi> of <hi>Darkneſs</hi> to the <hi>Judgment of the Great Day:</hi> So little Encouragement have we to truſt in Created <hi>reaſon.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:173120:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the third Head Propoſed, <hi>viz.</hi> The Nature of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE two main Hinges of this Debate, <hi>viz</hi> Concerning <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and concerning <hi>Revelation,</hi> as <hi>Above,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the 2d Head con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>Contrary</hi> to <hi>Reaſon</hi> having been ſo far Treated of; The further Diſcourſe of <hi>Myſtery</hi> may ſeem unneceſſary, ſeeing it is on both Parts agreed; <hi>Above,</hi> or <hi>contrary to Reaſon,</hi> demtermines <hi>Myſtery,</hi> or not <hi>Myſtery:</hi> But becauſe <hi>Myſtery, or not Myſtery</hi> bears the Face of the whole matter in Diſpute, and eſpecially, becauſe Reverence of the word of God, and of the Truths of it (as an <hi>Ark</hi> or <hi>Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> of, and for which, the Spirit of God hath <hi>Separated,</hi> and <hi>Sanctified</hi> the Word, <hi>Myſtery</hi>) It calls for a particular Reſearch, how, and to what Truths, and for what Ends It hath ſo Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated it: The Senſe or Significaaion of the word it ſelf may be derived from the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> where we meet with the plain notion of <hi>myſtery;</hi> the <hi>Moſaic</hi> Types are preſented, as <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious</hi> by the <hi>Veil</hi> thrown over <hi>Moſes's Face,</hi> even as the Apoſtle calls them <hi>Figures;</hi> ſo we read of <hi>Secret Things, Things kept ſecret; The ſecrets of Wiſdom; Proverbs,</hi> and the <hi>Interpretation</hi> of them; <hi>Parables; Dark Sayings of the Wiſe; Prophetic Viſions;</hi> All in Figures; ſome of them Interpreted, others left under their Veils: This O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of <hi>miſtery</hi> is worthy to be preferrd as moſt Pure, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; And there is a <hi>Hebrew</hi> word of very near found, comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the Senſe; though never ſo applied by the Sacred Text; <hi>viz.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which eaſily paſſes into the Greek, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: And yet it might fall in herewith; The word <hi>myſtery</hi> was a word known to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> to ſignify the Secreſies of <hi>Pagan</hi> Devotions, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated only to their <hi>myſtae,</hi> peculiar Devoted Perſons; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, thoſe Rites were fowl, and Idolatrous; The Spirit of God was pleaſed to take it from thoſe impure uſes, as the Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe and Hire of <hi>Tyrus,</hi> to be <hi>Holineſs</hi> to the <hi>Lord;</hi> to convey the Apprehenſion of the Secrecy of the Truths of the Goſpel, as <hi>Reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> in it by himſelf at that Time, that had been hidden before,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:173120:22"/> and at that very time, from thoſe who <hi>Believed not; the hidden Wiſdom of God</hi> ſpoken to them, who were the <hi>Perfect,</hi> or the Conſecrated <hi>Myſtae</hi> of it; Thus as God was pleaſed to <hi>ſeparate</hi> the <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 15.16.</note> and Sanctify them, as an <hi>Offering</hi> to <hi>Himſelf</hi> by the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> through the Preaching of the Apoſtles, who were before as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean;</hi> ſo he pleaſed alſo to Hallow this word <hi>myſtery,</hi> how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever impure in its former uſe, and to appoint it a <hi>Veſſel</hi> of <hi>Honour</hi> to himſelf. Let us now conſider the importance of it in the Sacred Writings of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> with the Reaſon of things that ſhall be Diſcourſed out of it, and Univerſal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of Language in it.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. The Spirit of God makes uſe of the word <hi>myſtery,</hi> in ſpeaking of the whole Frame, and Complex of the Goſpel; the Preaching of which is ſaid to be the <hi>Revelation of the myſtery,</hi> which had been <hi>hid in God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 16.27. 1 Cor. 29. c. 4. 1. Coloſ. 1.26.27.</note> 
                  <hi>The Preachers of the Goſpel are called Stewards of the mysteries of God;</hi> It is ſtiled <hi>the miſtery of Chriſt, the myſtery of Faith, the hidden Wiſdom of God in myſtery, Ordain'd to the glory of Saints, to whom it is given to know the myſteries of the Kingdom of God. This myſtery:</hi> Now this ſo often Repeated Denomination of the Goſpel by <hi>myſtery;</hi> not only, as before, but ſince the <hi>Rrvelation</hi> of it; and without any mention of <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> together with the calling it <hi>myſtery,</hi> ſhews. It is an Appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Spirit of God much Delights in, and hath made (as one may ſay) the very <hi>Title</hi> of the Goſpel; It is therefore very a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mazing; Any one who profeſſes a Veneration of its Records, ſhould be ſo Induſtrious and Buiſy to tear it off, and pull away this Seale: It is moſt true; <hi>Revelation</hi> hath much chang'd the State of <hi>myſteriouſneſs</hi> in the Goſpel, but hath not ſo Removed <hi>myſtery</hi> from it; but that there is principal Reaſon, that even ſurmounts the Clearer <hi>Revelation</hi> of it in the New Teſtament; why the Title is ſtill continued: For it is plain, <hi>myſtery</hi> may be in ſome ſenſe <hi>Revealed,</hi> and yet be <hi>myſtery</hi> ſtill, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that <hi>Revelation; Nebuchadnezzar</hi>'s <hi>Dream</hi> was in it ſelf a <hi>Revelation</hi> from God to that Proud Monarch;<note place="margin">Dan. 2.12.</note> and yet was <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stery,</hi> till Expounded by <hi>Daniel,</hi> becauſe not underſtood: So <hi>Daniel</hi>'s Viſions, when he himſelf <hi>underſtood not;</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Reſearched upon the things <hi>Revealed</hi> by God to them, what the <hi>Spirit of Chriſt in them did ſignify,</hi> and did not think
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:173120:22"/> it concern'd them not, becauſe they wanted <hi>Idea</hi>'s of what they underſtood not; Chriſt Taught by <hi>Parables,</hi> which were yet <hi>myſteries,</hi> till opened by him, and to all but thoſe to whom he opened them. The Book we call the <hi>Revelation;</hi> is ſtill <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous.</hi> This I urge, that the joyning the <hi>myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> with <hi>Revelation,</hi> may not be looked upon as proof ſufficient, it is no longer <hi>Miſtery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. There are particular Branches of Evangelical Truth, to which the Spirit of God is pleaſed peculiarly to apply <hi>myſtery;</hi> the firſt Scripture of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> in which we find it uſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.11. I reſerve for after conſideration,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>viz. The myſteries of the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> ſo of the <hi>myſtery of God and of the Father, and of Christ;</hi> Of which I will give a further Account in the cloſe of the Diſcourſe. The Mediatorſhip of Chriſt in the various Progreſſes of it to higheſt Glory, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main <hi>without Controverſy, the great myſtery of Godlineſs,</hi> till his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn in Glory; wherein It is moſt manifeſt, as there are ſome Points very Indiſputably, deeply <hi>myſterious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3.16.</note> as <hi>God mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in Fleſh, Juſtified in Spirit,</hi> So others more plain, <hi>as Preached to the Gentiles, believed on in the World,</hi> that, as to their out ſide, were plain matters of Fact. Yet theſe, as well as the others make up the <hi>great myſtery of Godlineſs;</hi> which ſhews there is ſome deep Reaſon in the Eye of the Divine Spirit, why the Notion, and Word, <hi>myſtery,</hi> ſhould be applied to each truth of the Goſyel, though ſome of thoſe truths are more plain,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.26.32.</note> than others: the Union betwixt Chriſt and his Church; and ſo with every Believing Soul is, what will be <hi>myſtery,</hi> till he <hi>preſent it to himſelf</hi> in every particular Member of it, <hi>à glorious Church, not having ſpot, or wrinckle;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 19.7.</note> which The <hi>Revelation</hi> ſtiles the <hi>Nuptials</hi> of the <hi>Lambs Wife,</hi> and the Marriage Supper of the <hi>Lamb;</hi> For who can declare this Union, rather inwardly perceived, than poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to be Expreſſed yet? The Final <hi>Recapitulation</hi> of all things in <hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> in Chriſt, that ſhall be Happy and Bleſſed, is ſtiled the <hi>myſtery of the Divine Will,</hi> and it is to be done in the grand <hi>Oeconomy</hi> of the <hi>Fullneſs of Times,</hi> or of all Time, when <hi>myſtery</hi> ſhall be <hi>Finiſhed;</hi> and before which, it ſhall not be <hi>Finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> but Remain <hi>miſtery</hi> till then, according to the Senſe of all Scripture. There are ſome great <hi>Propheticks</hi> of Scripture, as the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:173120:23"/> Fulneſs of the <hi>Gentile</hi> Churches, or their coming to a fuller Light after the Eclipſe of the <hi>Apoſtaſy</hi> by <hi>Antichriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 11.25. Epheſ. 3.3. 1 Cor. 15.51. Rev. 1.30. c. 10.7. 1 Cor. 13.1.2.</note> together with their whole number coming in, and making one Body with the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> or rather a <hi>Joynt Body;</hi> The <hi>myſtery</hi> ſpoken of the <hi>Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Living Saints</hi> at the coming of Chriſt; the <hi>myſtery</hi> of the <hi>ſeven Stars, and ſeven Candleſticks,</hi> and the <hi>myſtery</hi> of <hi>God Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed;</hi> of which, I fear, there are yet ſo low <hi>Idea</hi>'s in the general Profeſſors of Chriſtianity, that if ever they were <hi>myſteries,</hi> they are ſo ſtill; as particularly, to Inſtance in that of the Living Saints Changed; which we generally look upon, as if it meant no more, than the ſuddenneſs of a change equivalent to Death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thoſe Saints, who ſhall be Found Alive at the <hi>Coming of Chriſt;</hi> which is ſo far from a <hi>myſtery,</hi> that it cannot be otherwiie; the Coming of Chriſt being ſo Inſtantaneous, as Scripture every where declares it; which Aſſures, there lies a much deeper ſenſe under thoſe words; as comparing them with <hi>The Living, The Remaining,</hi> or rather, <hi>Reſerv'd,</hi> twice uſed, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.15, 17. will aſſure them, who cloſely conſider it; But I think it unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable any further to engage herein; only to obſerve the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance of the word <hi>Myſtery,</hi> in Scripture, to be That what it Reveals, as in the Sum and main Subſtance, hath yet unconceivable Receſſes, and Retirements of <hi>Truth;</hi> which we connot yet comprehend, or find <hi>Ideas</hi> of, and yet what it doth <hi>Reveal,</hi> is of great moment to us; and ought to fill us with a deſire of Fuller Comprehenſions of; as perfective of, not only of our Underſtandings, but makeing bleſſed our whole Man.</p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. There is yet remaining one uſe more the Scripture makes of the word, <hi>miſtery,</hi> in what, it doth not own, as <hi>myſtery</hi> of, or from it ſelf; but Blazons, as <hi>Counter-myſtery,</hi> to it ſelf; and ſo far as we ſuppoſe, the Holy Spirit transferr'd the uſe of the word <hi>myſtery</hi> from <hi>Pagan Idolatrous</hi> Impurity; it does in this one Inſtance Refund it, and place it on its own Baſe; And this is the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. And after leads us to the <hi>Land of Shinar,</hi> as the Baſe of it, <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the Great,</hi> on whoſe <hi>Forehead was written great myſtery,</hi> Rev. 17.7. And herein Scripture on one ſide teaches us the Senſe of <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery;</hi> that it ſignifies Coverture, and Concealment; For tho theſe two <hi>myſteries</hi> differ, as Heaven and Hell; for in one we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173120:23"/> have the <hi>Deeps of God;</hi> In the other are hid the deeps of <hi>Satan,</hi> though under the Name of a <hi>Catholick Church; Antichriſtianiſm</hi> under the Name of Chriſtianity; It teaches us therefore to Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor, to Aſcribe to Goſpel <hi>Myſtery,</hi> any of its Cheates, or Lyes; But in that this <hi>Mystery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity</hi> is not Conſum'd but by the <hi>Breath</hi> of <hi>Chriſt's Mouth,</hi> and the <hi>Glory</hi> of his <hi>Appearance;</hi> It ſhews the Goſpel ſhall continue <hi>Myſtery,</hi> while this <hi>Counter-my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> is ſufferr'd to Endure.</p>
               <p>§. But while we thus according to the Goſpel it ſelf ſpeake of it, as <hi>myſtery,</hi> and that the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity</hi> is a <hi>counter-myſtery</hi> to it; we Exalt the Wiſdom of it, as the <hi>Glorious Goſpel</hi> of the <hi>Bleſſed God, only Wiſe, Juſt, and Right,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 8.6 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 Sam. 2.3. 2 Pet. 1.16. c. 1.4. 1 Tim. 5 4. c. 4.7. c. 6.20.</note> 
                  <hi>the words of whoſe Lips are All in Righteouſneſs, and there is nothing Froward, nor Perverſe in them; His mouth ſpeaketh Truth, Wickedneſs is an abomination to his Lips.</hi> He is a <hi>God of Judgment; and by him All things are weighed:</hi> Nothing of <hi>Jargon,</hi> or <hi>Chymere;</hi> The Goſpel abhors <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,</hi> either <hi>thoſe cunningly deviſed, or Old Wives Fables, Endleſs gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alogies, oppoſitions of Science falſly ſo call'd.</hi> All theſe are peculiar to the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity, its Lyes and Deluſions</hi> after the <hi>manner of Satan, the Lyar from the beginning, and the Father of Lyes, the Baalzebul,</hi> and <hi>Baalzebub,</hi> the <hi>God</hi> of <hi>Dung,</hi> and of <hi>a Fly;</hi> but the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel are all of greateſt weight, <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> of Wiſdom and <hi>Truth;</hi> and hereof it gives aſſurance to all Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, who are not Blind Devotioniſts,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2.2.</note> but have <hi>All Riches of the Full Aſſurance of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> even in the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Goſpel, that are <hi>moſt ſablime;</hi> altho it be an Underſtanding of Faith, as hath been already, and ſhall be further ſhewn; yea, even thoſe, who by the Aſſiſtances of its General Grace, apply themſelves with Humility, and ſincere deſires of its Truth to the Word of God, find great Sweetneſs, and Satisfaction, and an unuſual Light ariſeth in Oppoſition to Darkneſs; <hi>The Entrance of thy Word giveth Light, it giveth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding</hi> to the <hi>Simple;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.13. Eccleſ. 5.1. 2 Tim. 3.7.</note> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is more Abhor'd by it, <hi>than Superſtition, the Sacrifice of Fools, the ſillyneſs of even Women, ever Learning, never able to come to the Knowledg of the Truth.</hi> All theſe things are to be remanded to <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> and are the Characters of the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity.</hi> Nor do the <hi>myſteries</hi> of Chriſtianity conſiſt in dark and cloudy Speculations, or thorny <hi>Scholaſtic</hi> Diſputes,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173120:24"/> thoſe oppoſitions of <hi>Science Falſely ſo call'd.</hi> They are rather the Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of Reaſon, that would bring down the <hi>myſteries</hi> of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel under it ſelf, and the Artifice of Sathan ſo to entangle them: whereas in their own pure Fountain, the Word of God, They are all <hi>profitable for Doctrine Reproof,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.17. Rom. 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>Inſtruction in the ways of Righteouſneſs,</hi> and that through <hi>the Patience</hi> and <hi>Comfort of the Scripture,</hi> we might <hi>have hope;</hi> and they make often an outward Reformation, where they have not the full ſaving Effect; <hi>Goſpel myſteries</hi> are not therefore the <hi>Monopoly,</hi> or the Engroſſment of a Profeſſion,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.12. 1 Cor. 4.1.</note> or a <hi>Prieſt-craft;</hi> every Chriſtian ought to Aſpire to be a <hi>Teacher;</hi> and the <hi>Faithful Stewards</hi> of theſe <hi>myſteries,</hi> to uſe utmoſt Diligence, they may be ſo, as the greateſt <hi>Seale</hi> of their own Miniſtry:<note place="margin">Acts 20.26.27. Col. 1.18. Jud. 12.13.</note> And <hi>woe to them,</hi> if they ſhun to that end, to <hi>declare</hi> fully the <hi>Counſel of God, Teaching every man, and Warning every man; that they may preſent every man perfect in Chriſt Jeſus; Not Wells without Water, or Clouds without Rain.</hi> It is only for Order and Government ſake, and in Truſt that this grand Office may be certainly Diſcharged, that there is a diſtinct <hi>Presbytery</hi> who are only worthy of <hi>double,</hi> or of any Honour at all, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their <hi>Labour in the Word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. v. 13.15.16.</note> 
                  <hi>and Doctrine, and watching Night and Day, to ſave themſelves, and thoſe that hear them:</hi> who might <hi>at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend on this very thing, and give themſelves wholly to Reading and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation</hi> for general Profit. A <hi>Guild for myſtery</hi> is only proper to the <hi>Craftſmen</hi> of <hi>Diana,</hi> the <hi>Merchants of Babylon, the Prieſts of Antichriſt; Falſe Apoſtles,</hi> whoſe Reproach thrown upon the Goſpel, <hi>Their Lord will Return</hi> upon them, and the Blood of Souls loſt by their Unfaithfulneſs in the diſcharge of their Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and to conclude this Branch, <hi>Goſpel Myſteries</hi> ſhall not be <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries</hi> for ever, but the perfect Comprehenſion of them is <hi>Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> for the <hi>Glory of Saints;</hi> and the Knowledg of them, tho not perfect here, yet ſhall end in the <hi>brightneſs of the Firmament</hi> to all the Wiſe in them; and They who <hi>Instruct</hi> in them <hi>ſhall ſhine as the Stars;</hi> whereas the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity</hi> ſhall be <hi>conſumed by the Brightneſs of the appearance of Chriſt, and the Miniſters of it go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Perdition;</hi> thoſe <hi>Planetory Stars</hi> are They, for whom is <hi>reſerved the Blackneſs of Darkneſs for ever,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. 12.3. 2 Theſ. 2.8.</note> Jud. 13.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. The Reaſon therefore of ſo cloſe adhering to the word, and notion of <hi>myſtery,</hi> is that high Reverence due to the very
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173120:24"/> word, the <hi>wiſdom</hi> of the <hi>Divine Spirit</hi> hath choſen,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.13. c. 1.10.</note> who <hi>compares Spiritual things with Spiritual;</hi> if Chriſtians ſhould <hi>ſpeak the ſame thing,</hi> as the Apoſtle Admoniſhes, who would not deſire to ſpeak the ſame word, the Spirit of God hath ſo often uſed! This is an Honour due to Scripture, and to the Holy Spirit the Author; but beyond this, the Goſpel Notion of <hi>myſtery</hi> Keeps up the Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence due to theſe great Truths, for the ſake of that <hi>Abyſſe</hi> of Wiſdom, Love and Grace, from whence they Flow, and puts us in mind always of their Original, and that Riches of Compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, making known what had elſe for ever lay hid; The ſenſe hereof keeps always low all proud Reflexions on our own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Holds in a conſtant dependence upon the Enlightning Grace of God; This keeps the Divine Life at the due Elevation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid up in Divine <hi>myſteries,</hi> and Iſſuing from them by the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livening Spirit of God, not Proſtrated to Fallen <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and its Power of Free Will, as at the Higheſt, but a more exalted <hi>Ethics,</hi> or <hi>Moral Philoſophy.</hi> Hereby the Truths Revealed in the word are kept ſafe from Sacrilegious Violation, or being Condemn'd at the Tribunal of corrupt <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but Enthron'd in <hi>myſtery</hi> far a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>reaſon;</hi> this Gives the Adequate Account of <hi>miracles,</hi> not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to aſſure, the <hi>Revelations</hi> they Sealed, were from God; but to ſhew a Supernatural Power, like themſelves, neceſſary to En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighten the Underſtanding, and to Sanctify the whole Spirit in conformity to them: This gives Reaſon to an Earneſt Deſire of that Eternal Life and Happineſs, <hi>the Exceeding and Eternal weight of Glory,</hi> ſhewn to be Incomprehenſible, as the Truths in which they are contain'd, and that lead thereunto, and which cannot be comprehended, till that <hi>finiſhing</hi> of <hi>myſteries</hi> in that <hi>Everlaſting Kingdom.</hi> Now all theſe Reaſons of Holding Faſt the <hi>Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> word, and Notion of <hi>myſtery,</hi> are as ſo many Countermines to the Artifices of Sathan, and his Inſtruments, to Deprive us of the Real Benefits of it, and therefore we ought to be Jealous over them for our own, and others ſake; leaſt, as the great Engineer of falſe <hi>Reaſon beguiled Eve</hi> with it,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 11.1.</note> ſo <hi>our minds</hi> ſhould be <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted</hi> from the Purity of Divine Truth, <hi>as It is in Chriſt.</hi> For thus <hi>Antiſcripturiſm</hi> and <hi>Superſtition</hi> mutually circulating one into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the Help of Human Reaſon and Imagination have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced <hi>Paganiſm, Antichriſtianiſm,</hi> and <hi>Mahometiſm,</hi> of which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timation was before made.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:173120:25"/>§. 6. To conclude then the whole concerning <hi>myſtery,</hi> as <hi>above Reaſon;</hi> that is, above our Fallen, Cor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>upted <hi>Reaſon;</hi> That great Oracle of our Lord, of which intimation was before made, gives us the ſum of the matter;<note place="margin">Mat. 13.11.12. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> he ſpeaking to his Diſciples, ſayth to them; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you it is given to know the myſteryes of the Kingdom of Heaven; To others it is not given:</hi> This is the Firſt occaſion, the Spirit of God was pleaſed to take, to make uſe of the word, <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery,</hi> in the New Teſtament: and it was before the calling of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> which gives a more Heauenly, and Divine Deſcent to the uſe of the word <hi>myſtery,</hi> than the taking it from the Familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity the <hi>Gentiles</hi> had with it,<note place="margin">Pſal. 49.4. Pſal. 78.2.</note> and accommodating the Language of the Goſpel to them; For it alludes to that of the <hi>Pſalm; I will open my mouth in a Parable, I will utter dark ſayings of Old.</hi> And it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied by Chriſt to the diſtinguiſhing Grace of God, giving to ſome to know theſe <hi>myſteries,</hi> and hiding them from others; <hi>To them it is not given;</hi> which is the moſt proper notion of <hi>myſtery</hi> in all Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages; the word <hi>myſtery</hi> Importing in univerſal uſe, a Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg in any thing peculiar to ſome, and not to others; and ſo this uſe of it by our Lord gives a principal Reaſon why Scripture chooſes this word; <hi>viz.</hi> to Magnify this very Grace; For if theſe Truths were in our Power, under our Command, or under our <hi>Reaſon,</hi> what neceſſity were there of <hi>giving</hi> to know, and how to ſome, and not to others? Who have yet the ſame things laid before 'em, but in <hi>ſeeing, ſee not;</hi> even as the <hi>Parable of the Sower</hi> which our Lord makes a Figure and Type of this diſtinguiſhing Grace: It was equally Offered, but <hi>Expounded Apart</hi> to the <hi>Diſciples:</hi> To thoſe to whom It was not Expounded, it was <hi>myſtery,</hi> becauſe they had the outſide, but <hi>ſeeing</hi> and <hi>hearing, ſaw not, heard not, to them It was not given;</hi> To the <hi>Diſciples,</hi> to whom it was Expounded, it was ſtill <hi>myſterious</hi> in one great ſenſe, becauſe they held it by the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure of Grace; they did not attain by their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but <hi>to them it was given.</hi> The <hi>Ideas</hi> were kept for them in the <hi>word of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> and from thence ſtill <hi>given</hi> them afreſh: <hi>to him that hath ſhall be given, and he ſhall have more abundance:</hi> The Spirit of God, as a higher mind, as that <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Revelation,</hi> upholds the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>Mind,</hi> Sanctifyed and Renewed in the Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Ballancing, Applying, Arguing, Inferring and Producing into holy Action; declaring within themſelves and to others in words, and giving them an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterance,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.1.</note> an Elocution proper to thoſe <hi>Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:173120:25"/> things,</hi> thoſe Truths; as he is called the <hi>Spirit giving utterance;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 2.3.</note> And thus in higheſt Senſe, thoſe Truths are <hi>myſterious,</hi> even ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Senſe of the Treatiſe, as being above <hi>Reaſon;</hi> For all thoſe, that attempt this Circuit by their own <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and Judg and Condemn by it, and will have the whole within the Cogniſance of their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> are ſo Dazled and amaz'd, that even the Advantages of the <hi>Reaſon,</hi> reſerved by general Grace, are taken from them; and they become deſpiſers, deniers, profeſſed Enemies to thoſe Truths, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>men of</hi> of <hi>Soul, Reaſon,</hi> that is, not having the Spirit; and ſo according to that ſevere Doom, That is <hi>Taken from them, even which they had;</hi> and what was <hi>above their Reaſon,</hi> thus becomes contrary to their <hi>Reaſon.</hi> And this is the concluſive Reaſon, why the Underſtanding, humble, Chriſtian can never part with <hi>myſtery, Goſpel-myſtery;</hi> what is held in <hi>myſtery</hi> is held by <hi>Grace,</hi> and not by <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> is their Title; how then ſhould they part with <hi>myſtery!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Of</hi> Reaſon <hi>and</hi> Myſtery <hi>united in their higheſt Elevation, in the</hi> Eternal Son of the Father; The Reaſon, The Myſtery.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>I Have intimated before,<note place="margin">The Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction into this chapter.</note> I ſhould have abandon'd in Sacred Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes, the ſo much abuſed word, <hi>Reaſon;</hi> were it not not for one tranſcendent Scripture; in which I am ſully perſwaded, the Divine Spirit hath on purpoſe ſingled out that word, the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 1.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> the Reputed <hi>Princes of the wiſdom of the world,</hi> among the <hi>Greeks</hi> (whom the Apoſtle Remarks for <hi>ſeeking after wiſdom</hi>) have unver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally Expreſſed it by; that is, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, now of this the <hi>Evangeliſt John</hi> in Spirit makes choice to Expreſs the <hi>only begotten Son of God,</hi> by; and I ſhall endeavour to make plain, by this word, he intends <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Wiſdom,</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> in the firſt place: and becauſe this Sonſhip of the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> or <hi>Reaſon</hi> is higheſt <hi>myſtery,</hi> the ſame Apoſtle <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.12, 13. is Inſpir'd to joyn the <hi>Name, he hath written, which no man knoweth, but He himſelf, with the Name whereby He is called, The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of God.</hi> So uniting <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> in him; as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays, what is the Name of God, and <hi>what is his Sons Name, if thou canſt tell?</hi> the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son dwell</hi> alike in the <hi>Light, to which none can
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:173120:26"/> Approach.</hi> To ſhew therefore how in the higheſt <hi>Reaſon</hi> the higheſt <hi>myſtery</hi> concenters, ſhall be the undertaking of this chapter; that I may bring <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> to the happieſt Conſpiration, and no more diſpute between them; I know the undertaking is high, and difficult, but by the Aſſiſtance of <hi>The Wiſdom, The Reaſon,</hi> of whom I am to ſpeak, I will proceed.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. The Wiſe of the <hi>Pagan</hi> Nations had not two greater Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, or words, than <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Mystery;</hi> the one expreſſing <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Wiſdom,</hi> or Religion; and the other as Communicated to their peculiar Followers, or Diſciples, and wrapp'd up in ſecret Figures, or <hi>Cabalas; Supernatural Wiſdom,</hi> and manifeſtation from their Gods; In both they were extreamly Fooliſh, and Deceiv'd; as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dreadfully Corrupted, and Defiled: Theſe two, yet the <hi>wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> of God and his <hi>Grace</hi> in Jeſus Chriſt, hath laid hold upon in the Goſpel, according to ſome former delineations in the Old Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament; yet taking in thoſe <hi>Gentile</hi> Notions, and words alſo as ſuited to them, when Grace broke out upon them in their <hi>Calling;</hi> as hath been already ſhown in <hi>myſtery,</hi> and now ſhall be in <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and then both Applyed to our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. That the word, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, is in our <hi>Tranſlation</hi> given, and Received, and by long uſe ſettled <hi>[The word]</hi> is ſo known, it may ſeem a Boldneſs to offer at ſuch a change as to Interpret it, <hi>[The Reaſon]</hi> but beſides, that Grave, and Learned Interpreters have not differ'd much, as ſhall be after ſhewn; and that, there ſhall alſo be due Reverence in the Progreſs, given to that <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation [The Word]</hi> I do with greater Authority ſo Expound, ſuſtain'd therein by a paralel of the <hi>Beloved Diſciple</hi> with <hi>Solomon</hi> the <hi>Jedidiah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 8.22. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>Beloved of God;</hi> the Expreſſions are Uniform, as from the ſame Spirit intending the ſame Truth; yet making more Full, and plain by the Latter, what was not ſo fully made known by the Former; as the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> in its <hi>Parrheſia, Plainneſs,</hi> or openneſs of Speech, as in clearneſs of Light, excells <hi>The Old Teſtament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. That <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> differ only in ſound, or ſome very thin Diſtinction one from another, I think none will deny; who will not allow, the wiſeſt Man hath, and is the greateſt <hi>Reaſon?</hi> or that he who hath the moſt, or beſt <hi>Reaſon,</hi> hath the moſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and is the wiſeſt man? The ſame things then, that <hi>Solomon,</hi> aſcribeth to <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> The <hi>Evangeliſt John</hi> by the ſame Spirit, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes to the <hi>Reaſon;</hi> The <hi>Wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of it ſelf, as diſtinct from God,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:173120:26"/> and yet, as hath been ſhewn, Supreme, Abſtract, Infinite <hi>wiſdom,</hi> cannot be divided from God; It muſt be on with him: The <hi>Reaſon</hi> is ſpoken of by the <hi>Evangelist John,</hi> as diſtinct from God, and yet <hi>was God;</hi> The <hi>wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of it ſelf, as <hi>in the Beginning, from Everlasting,</hi> before the Creation; The <hi>Evangeliſt John</hi> ſpeaks of The <hi>Reaſon in the Beginning;</hi> and neceſſarily before the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, becauſe <hi>All things were made by him, and without him was not any Thing made, that was made. The wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of it ſelf, <hi>poſſeſſed by God, cloſe by him, with him; The Reaſon was with God, The ſame was with God; The wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of it ſelf, as <hi>brought up with God,</hi> a word of higheſt Senſe, expreſſing the <hi>ſame Life; The Reaſon,</hi> as before, <hi>was with God, was God; In him was Life; The Wiſdom</hi> ſpeaks of it ſelf, as <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited with God in the Creation, The Lord by wiſdom Founded the Earth; By underſtanding he Eſtabliſhed the Heavens;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>The wiſdom was there, when he ſet a compaſs on the Face of the Deep;</hi> Of the Reaſon it is ſaid as before, <hi>All Things were made by him; and without him was not any thing made, that was made: The VViſdom</hi> ſpeaks it ſelf, <hi>as brought forth, ſet up; Of the Reaſon</hi> It is ſaid; <hi>we Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held his Glory, as the Glory of the only Begotten of the Father, full of Truth,</hi> that is, <hi>wiſdom,</hi> as before Explained; The <hi>wiſdom</hi> ſaith of it ſelf, <hi>I was daily his delight, rejoycing always before him:</hi> The Goſpel ſaith ſeveral <hi>Times</hi> of the <hi>Reaſon; This is my Beloved Son, In whom I am well pleaſed. The VViſdom</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rejoycing in the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitable Parts of his Earth, and my Delights were with the Sons of Men.</hi> Of the <hi>Reaſon</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>He was made Fleſh, and came, and dwelt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us;</hi> all theſe Paralelliſms plainly ſhew; <hi>this Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>this Reaſon</hi> are the ſame; And He is <hi>That Word,</hi> who is ſaid to be <hi>Living, Powerful, ſharper than a two edged Sword,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">Heb. 4.12. Rev. 1.16.</note> And that awful Perſon, That <hi>He, with whom we have to do,</hi> as he hath it, and it <hi>cometh out of his Mouth,</hi> ſo it is the <hi>Sword</hi> with <hi>two Edges,</hi> ſo <hi>ſharp</hi> as to <hi>divide between the Senſe</hi> and <hi>Spirit;</hi> and all things are immediately <hi>open</hi> and <hi>manifeſt</hi> and <hi>naked in its ſight,</hi> becauſe in <hi>his ſight,</hi> whoſe word it is, and who is himſelf, the ſupreme <hi>word</hi> and <hi>wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. The word of God, as ſpoken, and written, and given out from <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> gives together with thoſe truths, that are above the Illumination of the Firſt Creation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Myſteries,</hi> All thoſe Truths, that are ſo juſt, and level to the Intellectual Nature of Man, as he was made in <hi>Knowledg, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs</hi> and <hi>True Holineſs;</hi> that tho they are much obſcur'd, and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:173120:27"/> effac'd, and many of them loſt, and the Ability to Form <hi>Idea</hi>'s and Apprehenſions of them in ſome almoſt, and in ſome alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether extinguiſhed; Yet partly by the Reſerve, Jeſus Chriſt, as the <hi>Eternal VViſdom,</hi> and the <hi>Son of the Father in Love and Grace,</hi> as well, as <hi>Truth,</hi> and as the Redeemer hath made; and partly by the Enforcing, and Invigorating that Light, Thoſe Truths cannot, but be acknowledged by the Mind, and Conſcience of Man; ſo far as to condemn the Violation of them by Evil Practiſes, and to Reſtrain thoſe Evil Practiſes, and to make better Human Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, and Manners: Therefore they appear abſolutely neceſſary for Human Society, and to paſs into Laws; but that excellent and Illuſtrious Light in which they at firſt ſhone out, ſo as that the Mind and Spirit ſhould taſt the full ſweetneſs, and perfectly reſign to them, is not Reſtored, but by a Supernatural Re-Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, and Renovation; in which regard even thoſe Truths, whoſe Implantation, and the Power of Forming Ideas of them, were at the firſt Natural, are now become Supernatural and <hi>myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious,</hi> and require a new Writing in the Heart, as to the firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency and Spirituality of them.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. The Eternal <hi>Wiſdom, Reaſon</hi> and Word by the Light, and Spirit, with which they are given, gives Teſtimony to thoſe truths of the Firſt Creation in the Heart of Man, ſo far as they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, ſuſtained, enforced, according to the Firſt Implantation or Writing in the Heart; and then it receives Teſtimony from them to thoſe ſupernatural Truths, that it delivers together with them; As he it is that <hi>Finds out the Knowledg of witty Inventions;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">As Letters, writing, Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> All that we admire ſo much, and that have obtained general Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation, and Uſe; and make ſo honourable the memory of the firſt Inventors in what Science, or Art ſoever, are from him, as the Supreme Original: In all theſe we hold our <hi>Reaſon</hi> by Him, who is above our <hi>Reaſon, even him, who hath that Name, which none knows but he himſelf;</hi> who is therefore ſupreme <hi>Myſtery,</hi> we hold all by Grace from him, how unthankful then is it to hold up our <hi>Reaſon</hi> againſt the Grace, againſt him by whom we hold it? or againſt the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of Him, and His Grace? For there is not an <hi>Idea</hi> rightly Formed, nor one true Ratiocination, not one witty Invention for good uſe; not one Righteous Law, or wiſe Decree; but it is, (as things are now,) by Grace through the Mediator, and from him, as the <hi>Saviour</hi> thus far of <hi>All Men,</hi>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:173120:27"/> and in theſe Regards, <hi>Taſting Death for every Man;</hi> but though the <hi>World</hi> was at <hi>firſt made by him,</hi> and is yet upheld; yet this <hi>great Light Shineth by his word in Darkneſs, and the Darkneſs comprehends it not,</hi> knows not him from whom it comes: No, not altho the Firſt Engravings of the Law on our Hearts are ſo far, as they are, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, or Re-enlightened by him; and tho with ſuch a variety, and free Diſpoſe to ſome, and not to others; Yet They to whom greateſt meaſures are given, except a higher Grace be given alſo, thro' the great Degeneracies of Human Nature, lift up thoſe high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er meaſures of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> higheſt againſt him; which plainly ſhews how little <hi>Reaſon</hi> can effect by it ſelf in things above ſuch an Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, as is given to it.</p>
               <p n="6">§. 6. As our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Father is, as in all Intellectual Beings, <hi>Reaſon</hi> is, an Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial word within the mind it ſelf; and as he Declares the <hi>Father</hi> by Inſpirations of Creation, and Mediatory Suſtentations of all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual Beings in their Intellectual Irradiations, and Motions; ſo he in a Supreme Government, and Conduct by his Spirit, hath Iſſued out into all thoſe Declarations by his <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles</hi> and other Servants of his, peculiarly Employed by him, which when ſpoken, and as now Collected into Scripture, we call <hi>the word of God;</hi> the ſubſiſtence to which the Eternal <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Father</hi> gives; <hi>Chriſt yeſterday, to day, the ſame for ever.</hi> And as he is in that word, the ſupreme Self-ſubſiſtent <hi>Word,</hi> ſo he hath made known all Supernatural Truths, Truths of the <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and flowing from Redemption by his Declarative Word in the Scriptures, the ſame word that gives the firſt, gives the other alſo; and the very Truths themſelves of that Supernatural Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Excellency have bright Beams of thoſe firſt truths, eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally united to them, throughout ſhining within them, Spark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out of Them, and round about Them; by which they may be known to be of God, and are by their Weight, by their Purity, by their Heavenlyneſs, by their entire Excellency Diſtinguiſhable from the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity:</hi> Thus we find the Goſpel of Chriſt, as full of Supernatural Truths,<note place="margin">Phil. 4.8.</note> ſo full of what ever is <hi>Lovely, True, Honeſt, Vertuous, of Good Report, worthy of Praiſe;</hi> even whole, univerſal moſt unſpotted Morality; and the Supernatural Truths themſelves are Orient with the ſame, far eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way above the Faded, Blaſted, Wither'd <hi>Ideas,</hi> or glozed Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances of thoſe, who have ſpoken moſt Excellingly of them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:173120:28"/> that Light: And herein is the <hi>Condemnation,</hi> that men receive not ſupernatural Truths; They Recoile, not from the Supernaturalneſs, but from the very Holineſs, Strictneſs, Purity, they are dazled with; even that, which was Implanted in Firſt Creation; They <hi>Love Darkneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 3.19.</note> 
                  <hi>rather than Light,</hi> becauſe <hi>their Deeds are Evil;</hi> and make a pretence of Prejudice againſt the Supernaturalneſs, and that they have not Aſſurance ſuch Truths are from God, to ſhelter the <hi>Evil Works,</hi> to which they adhere, and upon which theſe Truths Shine ſo <hi>warm</hi> and <hi>bright,</hi> and ſo ſharply Reproove; And thus the Goſpel of Chriſt firſt gives Teſtimony to all Implanted Truth, ſhewing to Man all that was <hi>written</hi> in his <hi>Heart;</hi> fills up the Vacuities, and Empty Spaces; gives new Light, and Beauty to the Defaced, and loſt Characters; ſo that men may know in their own Conſciences, It is that Firſt writing Reſtor'd, and they find it ſo undeniably within themſelves to be ſo, that they cannot deny it: And then Supernatural Truths ſo eſſentially united to Implanted, and Both ſo Circulating one within another, Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Truths Receive Teſtimony from thoſe Implanted Truths, that if the one are ſo undoubtedly from God, the other muſt be alſo; and no one can reject revealed Truth, but he muſt firſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obey, and Rebel againſt Natural, and therein is Juſtly and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly Condemn'd.</p>
               <p n="7">§. 7. Upon the whole then, we may from Jeſus Chriſt the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eme <hi>Reaſon, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the Supreme <hi>Myſtery</hi> derive this T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ain, and connexion of Truths. 1. That <hi>Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Soberneſs,</hi> being in the moſt inward Senſe of Mans mind, the principal Points of true <hi>Reaſon;</hi> where ever they are found at fulleſt Dimenſions and ſtrongeſt Excellency, Thre is higheſt <hi>Reaſon</hi> now, in the cleareſt Light, and Harmony, and the proper Language of it; Theſe are ſo found in the word of God, above the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the Natural Implanted Knowledg of God, now ſo obſcur'd, and ecclipſed by mans ſin, and Fall; and above that excellent Light Creation Gives, as <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 19. upon the compare gives the preference to the word of God above the Knowledg given from the <hi>Speech</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> 2. Who ever therefore is the Author of that Word is the Supreme Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, <hi>Reaſon and Word of God;</hi> and that is <hi>Jeſus Chriſt the Son of the Father in Truth, Full of Truth; the Living Word of God, whoſe Name is called, The word of God.</hi> 3. That he, who is the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme <hi>Reaſon, Wiſdom, Truth and word of God,</hi> as He is He by whom
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:173120:28"/> 
                  <hi>All was made,</hi> ſo He is He, by whom all is Conſerved, and Reſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; <hi>The Son of the Father in Love, as well as Truth, and full of Grace, as well as Truth.</hi> 4. He therefore,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.23.</note> as he is himſelf Supreme <hi>Myſtery,</hi> and is therefore called <hi>Faith,</hi> which is the <hi>Reaſon</hi> Superna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalized for <hi>Myſtery;</hi> ſo he Reveals the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Counſel</hi> of the Independent Will and Grace of the Father. 5. He Reſerves and Continues all the Light of the Firſt Illumination by Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, that is found, even where there is no Knowledg of Him; All the Learning in Arts, Sciences, and <hi>witty Inventions;</hi> He Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes All that Light, and Knowledg, <hi>Receiving</hi> for, and <hi>giving Gifts even to the Rebellious,</hi> under the Profeſſion of his Goſpel,<note place="margin">Pſal. 68.18.</note> 
                  <hi>that the Lord God may have a Tabernacle among them.</hi> 6. But Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, He as the <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> Inſtructs Savingly all his own Servants, and by <hi>inward Light,</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> communicated to them, Transfers, by his Spirit, from his word Supernatural with all Natural Truths into their Hearts; ſo that they are at once, The only true Men of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>Myſtae,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the <hi>Inſtructed in the My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries of the Kingdom of Heaven:</hi> So that as in Chriſt himſelf Supreme Wiſdom, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> Truth, and Supreme <hi>Mystery,</hi> (whom <hi>none Knoweth but the Father, and they to whom the Father Reveals Him) Reaſon, and Mystery are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited;</hi> ſo in All true Chriſtians <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Mystery</hi> dwell together; All Natural and Supernatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Truth according to Godlineſs, but Supernaturally given, and Communicated by an Illumination after the manner of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of <hi>Myſtery.</hi> 7. Through the Deluſion of Sathan un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Vizor of Chriſtianity hath ſprung up by falling from the Supreme <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the True <hi>Myſtery,</hi> the <hi>myſtery of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and Antichriſt the Son of Perdition;</hi> as the <hi>Pagans</hi> of old, Fell from Natural <hi>Truth,</hi> into <hi>Idolatry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">§. 8. But becauſe He, who is the <hi>Supreme Wiſdom, Reaſon, Truth,</hi> and by whom all things were made, and whoſe Name is the <hi>word of God,</hi> hath a <hi>Title written on his veſture, and on his Thigh; King of Kings, and Lord of Lords;</hi> There ſhall be a Kingdom of Higheſt Illumination, and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> the <hi>Inheritance of the Saints in Light,</hi> a Kingdom of <hi>Redemption, the World to come of the ſecond</hi> Adam, wherein all <hi>myſtery,</hi> Natural and Supernatural ſhall be <hi>Finiſhed,</hi> or fully laid Open, and Underſtood; and then the <hi>my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity</hi> ſhall be wholly <hi>Deſtroyed;</hi> when not only the Faculties of the Mind ſhall be Perfectly Reſtored by Renovation but the Organs of the <hi>Spiritual Body,</hi> fitted to the Action of the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:173120:29"/> Spirit; and the Divine Being ſhall be ſeen in the <hi>Eternal Son, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manuel,</hi> in our Nature, ſo far as it is poſſible for a Finite Being to comprehend an Infinite;<note place="margin">John 17.21.23.</note> to which alſo in and by him Saints ſhall be United.</p>
               <p n="9">§. 9. Thus all Wiſdom, <hi>Reaſon</hi> and Truth circulates with it ſelf in the Eternal <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and all his Oeconomy in his making the World; in the Government of it; in the Reſerves of Truth and Reaſon in the mind of Man in any Degree now; in the perfect Purity of the Word of God; and in the <hi>World to come,</hi> or Kingdom of the Eternal <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>word of God;</hi> ſo that we may Argue from the one to the other with great Aſſurance: If there be Wiſdom in the Laws of Creation, and Providence there are certainly Laws of Holineſs, Righteouſneſs and Soberneſs, every way correſpond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them; the Fear of the Lord in man; Departure from Evil cannot but anſwer the <hi>Ballancing the Clouds,</hi> and the <hi>weights for the wind,</hi> &amp;c. If we have any ſuch Laws of Wiſdom, and Equity in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kind, there is an entire Syſtem and Complex of Each, if an Infraction had not been made by Sin. On the other part if there be a Renovation of the Laws of inward and outward Holineſs, in and by the Redemption of Chriſt, and the <hi>New Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in <hi>his Redeemed;</hi> The <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of the <hi>Creation,</hi> wherein ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it <hi>Grones,</hi> and Travels in Pain until now, and the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of its Government ſhall be as Glorious; when it ſhall be <hi>Delivered from the Bondage of vanity and corruption,</hi> whereunto it was,<note place="margin">Rom 8.20.</note> and yet is Subject, by Reaſon of him who ſo Subjected it in Hope, into the <hi>Glorious Liberty of the Children of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">§. 10. As every <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> together with the Speech and Expreſſion, it hath, and makes of it ſelf, hath a certain <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergy</hi> and Force, or Spirit, that it powerfully ſends forth and works on others by; ſo it is Attributed to the <hi>Eternal wiſdom, Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and <hi>word of God to Powre out his Spirit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 1.23. c. 14. Joh. c. 15.16.</note> to ſend the <hi>Paraclet,</hi> or <hi>Comforter, the Holy Spirit,</hi> whom the Father ſends in the <hi>Sons Name,</hi> who is called the <hi>Spirit of that Word,</hi> by whom the <hi>world was made,</hi> the Spirit of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> of <hi>Revelation, The Spirit of the Son, The Spirit of Chriſt;</hi> and which was given upon the <hi>Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification</hi> of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Iohn 7.30.</note> the Spirit of Chriſt in the Prophets, and whom Scripture Introduces on all Accounts, as the Spirit Breathing in, and with the Declared <hi>Word of God;</hi> and <hi>Revealing the Myſteries
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:173120:29"/> of the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> that cannot otherwiſe be knwon; and yet this Spirit none can know but they who have it;<note place="margin">John 14.17</note> Thus in all things appears the Happy Union of <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> in the <hi>Supreme Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> and <hi>Word,</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Of the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of the <hi>Father, The Word, The Spirit,</hi> In whom the Goſpel gives the moſt Explicate, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummate Manifeſtation of <hi>Eternal Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>THE former Parts of this Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Myſtery</hi> hath neceſſarily led to the diſtinct conſideration of God; <hi>The Father of Lights</hi> and of Spirits;<note place="margin">The Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction.</note> All Beings of <hi>Reaſon</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending from Him. Of The Son of the Father in Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Eternal wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon;</hi> and <hi>in Love; The Word</hi> declaring the <hi>Father; Full of Grace, Full of Truth;</hi> Of The <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>wiſdom,</hi> of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> of <hi>Power;</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> giving <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tterance;</hi> The <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>VVord,</hi> (who is the <hi>Son,</hi>) and the <hi>Spirit</hi> are plainly Aſſured to us in Scripture to be <hi>ONE:</hi> Herein is higheſt <hi>Mystery;</hi> as a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion therefore of this Diſcourſe, Let us in very Brief conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them ſo; and the rather, becauſe One cannot but ſuſpect, This <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres Treatiſe, Chriſtianity not myſterious,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.8.</note> was deſigned to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> this great Truth; The Diſcourſes of which, however keeping cloſe to Scripture, it Stiles <hi>p.</hi> 25. <q>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagancies about the Trinity; and that Period, <hi>pag.</hi> 29. Savors ſtrongly of the fame <hi>Leven:</hi> But what do they mean by Conſiſting with themſelves, yet not with our common No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? Four may be called Five in Heaven, but ſo only the Name is chang'd; the thing remains the ſame: And ſince in this World, we cannot know any thing, but by our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Notions; How ſhall we be ſure of this Pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency between our preſent ſeeming Contradictions, and the
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:173120:30"/> Theology of the World to come?</q> In Anſwer hereunto in this great point, let us conſider.</p>
               <p n="1">§. 1. It is certain, an intellectual Spirit cannot be made ſuch, but that the Infinite, Intellectual Object, and moſt Intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible; GOD; muſt needs be ſeen in his great Glory, and Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of Perfection by it: But he cannot yet be <hi>found out to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection,</hi> but ſtill <hi>dwells in that Light,</hi> to which <hi>no one can Approach,</hi> both in regard of Infinity, and Infinite Holineſs and Spirituali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;<note place="margin">Job. 4.3.</note> ſo as to <hi>Charge</hi> pureſt Created Beings with <hi>Folly;</hi> to <hi>put no Truſt</hi> in the <hi>Holyeſt</hi> of his <hi>Servants;</hi> and the <hi>Stars</hi> are not <hi>pure in his ſight:</hi> The moſt Bleſſed of Created Spirits <hi>cover</hi> not only their <hi>Feet,</hi> but their <hi>Faces,</hi> and <hi>cast their Crowns before him:</hi> Even thoſe who are not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Iſa. 6.2. 2 Pet. 3.17. Jud. v. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Defirmamented;</hi> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Stars.</hi> Who have not <hi>Left their firſt Eſtate, nor forſaken their own Habitation;</hi> They dare not ſtand on their Intellectual, or Moral Accompliſhments: <hi>How much leſs they who dwell in Houſes of Clay, whoſe Foundation is in the Duſt,</hi> who are but <hi>worms.</hi> The <hi>Author of the Treatiſe</hi> we are upon, acknowledges, we have not <hi>Adequate conceptions of the Divine Being,</hi> and yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies <hi>Myſtery,</hi> becauſe not above Reaſon; not conſidering, That we muſt now by Faith, that Intellectual Grace of the <hi>New Creation,</hi> and of Divine Illumination, and therefore neceſſarily above the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of the Firſt Creation, if entire; much more, as fallen, come to <hi>God; Believing, He is, and is a Rewarder of them,</hi> who <hi>Diligently ſeek him:</hi> That is; To know him in the Mediator, and in the Light of his Divine Spirit, according to the Revelation of his Word.</p>
               <p n="2">§. 2. This Revelation of Scripture is ſo clear and full through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, eſpecially the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> that it cannot be Denied: There are ſo many, and ſo diſtinct Namings of them, both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and together: <hi>The Father, The Word</hi> (who is the <hi>Son) The Spirit;</hi> They are ſo Diſtinguiſhed One from the Other, and yet their Union one to another, is moſt Illuſtriouſly made known; as in this one Inſtance; the Spirit is Stiled, <hi>The Spirit, who proceeds from the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14. c. 15. c. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>whom the Father ſends in the Sons Name;</hi> Now the <hi>Father,</hi> as he is the <hi>Father,</hi> cannot be the <hi>Son;</hi> SO the <hi>Spirit</hi> is ſtiled, <hi>The Spirit, whom the Son ſends from the Father; The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:173120:30"/> who Glorifies Chriſt; The Spirit of the Son, The Spirit of Chriſt;</hi> And we know, <hi>The Son</hi> cannot be <hi>The Father,</hi> as he is the <hi>Son;</hi> when therefore, as the Apoſtle Expreſly Affirms, The <hi>Spirit</hi> is the <hi>One</hi> and the <hi>Self Same Spirit;</hi> and he is continually ſtiled, the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> whom moſt of the Adverſaries acknowledg <hi>one with God,</hi> as the Spirit of a man is one with himſelf; and that yet the <hi>Spirit is the Spirit of the Father,</hi> and <hi>of the Son,</hi> It is abſolute Scripture De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration, that <hi>the Father, the Son, the Spirit</hi> are both moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct, and yet moſt truly, <hi>The One true God;</hi> Their Attributes are Diſtinct to Each, and yet the ſame Divine Perfections ſhine out alike in All; Their Acts of Love and Grace in the Salvation of man, are ſo diſtinct, and yet proper only to the <hi>One Eternal Being,</hi> as the Fountain of them; That they, from whom thoſe Emanations are, cannot but be underſtood, as Diſtinct, and yet but One. The ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgments, and Returns, that are called for from, and made by Redeemed Saints, unto the <hi>Father, the Son, the Spirit,</hi> are ſuch as can only be Required by the moſt High God to himſelf, nor without Horrible, and Abominable Idolatry yeilded to any other: The Goſpel is ſo Abundant in all theſe, and makes this manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God ſo principal an end, and ſcope of all its Diſcourſes, and places ſo much its Glory in it, as in what it moſt deſigns to declare; That if we own it to be a <hi>Revelation</hi> from God, it is as great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury either to reject or to interpret it contrary to it ſelf herein; (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our ſhort and corrupt Reaſon cannot allow it) as to impute any monſtrous Thing to it: For it muſt be ſuppoſed either to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal ſome ſuch Portent as cannot be Believed; or that it knows ſo little how to expreſs it ſelf, that wherein it ſpeaks, as fully as plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without a Figure, as conſtantly as may be, it muſt yet be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rul'd by Interpretation, and Taught to Speak; or elſe it would ſpeak ſo, as to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un men into Idolatry, and Blaſphemy againſt the <hi>One true God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">§. 3. If then, <hi>the Father, the Word, the Spirit</hi> be a Revelation of the Divine Being to us from it ſelf; we dare not but Acknowledg it Infinite <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> becauſe we acknowledg the Divine Being to be ſo; and becauſe the very Titles, and Eſſential Attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of each <hi>are ſo; the Father of Lights is he, with whom is no variation or ſhadow of turning; the Eternal Wiſdom, Reaſon, and Word the Son is he, in whom is Light, the true Light, the Truth: The Spirit is the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth,</hi> of <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> of <hi>Holineſs;</hi> and becauſe from them is the Manuduction into All Wiſdom, and Truth; Every <hi>Good</hi> and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:173120:31"/> 
                  <hi>Perfect Gift</hi> comes from <hi>the Father;</hi> The Son is, the <hi>true Light,</hi> the <hi>Light of Men; the Spirit leads into all Truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">§. 4. Yet is this great Truth of the Ineffable Union, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, and yet Diſtinction, Profoundeſt <hi>Myſtery;</hi> in Regard of the Revelation of ſuch a <hi>Deep of God;</hi> the Imperfect Knowledg we have of it; and the neceſſity of Divine Illumination, and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication unto Adoration, Love, Service, Obedience <hi>of Faith,</hi> ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to it.</p>
               <p n="5">§. 5. Yet it is not to be Reproached, as <hi>Jargon,</hi> or the <hi>Chymera</hi> of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or other <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Falſhoods; For the Saints and Servants of this great Truth have a <hi>full aſſurance</hi> in it, tho a <hi>Myſtery;</hi> and whereas it ſeems to encounter the Unity of the Divine Being, or the Notion we have of <hi>One</hi> and <hi>Three;</hi> Faith Enlightned by the Divine Spirit ſees ſo many more great Principles of Truth and Holyneſs Centring in it, that it conſiders we are no more able to Judg of Unity in Him, (who is All, and not a poor, ſingle Unite,) than a Child is able to know, an Unite is the Beginning and Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Number; nor according to our Low <hi>Arithmetic,</hi> to judg of the Application of <hi>Three</hi> to the <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Spirit</hi> the <hi>One God;</hi> ſo Supreme, Glorious, Remoov'd from All Approach of Created Being; than a Child can <hi>work by the Rule of Three;</hi> Only we know in him, it muſt be Perfection of Being, and Operation. And as <hi>Abraham,</hi> in the <hi>Sacrificing Iſaac,</hi> was taught to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance that Natural Principle of Parental Affection, and even of Oracle;<note place="margin">Heb. 11.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>In</hi> Iſaac <hi>ſhall thy ſeed be Called;</hi> by that therein more Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mount Light of Faith; <hi>God was able to raiſe him from the Dead, from whence he Received him in a Figure:</hi> So are true Believers by that great Light of Faith enabled in thoſe ſo Reſplendent Beams of Revelation before mention'd, to Adore the One God in the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> the <hi>Son</hi> and the <hi>Spirit; tho they underſtand and ſpeak but as Children, and ſee through a Glaſs Darkly, till they come to ſee Face to Face; and to know, as they are known,</hi> or ſhall be then <hi>made to know;</hi> and if there are thoſe <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Anak</hi> in Reaſon, as they ſeem to themſelves, that cannot receive it, we Adore with the <hi>Son of the Father</hi> in our Nature; <hi>I thank thee, Oh Father, Lord of Heaven, and Earth; that thou haſt hid theſe Things from the Wiſe, and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 10.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and haſt Revealed them to Babes; even ſo Father, for ſo it ſeemed good in thy ſight. Lord open thou our Eyes, that we may behold the Wonders of the Myſteries of the Truth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 110.18. 1 Tim. 1.17.</note> Now to the King, <hi>Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, Inviſible, the only wiſe God, be Glory for Ever.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:173120:31"/>
            <head>A LETTER In <hi>POSTSCRIPT</hi> TO THE Author of the Treatiſe on his Second Edition, with Enlargements, and the Addition of His Name.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>JUST, as the very laſt of the preceding Diſcourſe was Print<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off, your Second Edition came to my Hand with your Name prefixed; which to me, makes no Alteration; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Name of a Perſon wholly unknown to me; nor do I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire (as I ſaid at firſt) to make any Enquiry; For, be it never ſo Great, it can add no weight to the main importance of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, which is a purſuit after Truth; nor can any ſuppoſable Diminution (tho I ſuppoſe none) Abate the Intrinſic value of Any Argument: I leave that therefore to its Juſt value with any, that know it; The Regard, and Deference, The Book may ſeem to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve Right to, on the Account of a Second Edition, in my Judgment, depends wholly on the <hi>Sterlyn</hi> worth of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe it ſelf; For if that be Maſſy, and of the Alloy of Truth; it is an Honour to thoſe, who have ſo great a Guſt of it, as well as to the Diſcourſe, that ſo well Deſerves; If That, being on ſo High a Point, have not juſt Merit, it is only a Character of the Degeneracy, and Irreligion, as well, as the Inſipience of the Many of the Age: Leaving therefore thoſe things that have no Intereſt in the preſent concern, I come to what is more material.</p>
            <p>And in the firſt place, I would, with all due modeſty Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate to you the method, I have obſerv'd in order to the Anſwer of your Treatiſe; which hath not been I confeſs, to Follow you, as they ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Paragraph</hi> by <hi>Paragraph;</hi> that I might avoid any ſmall inſignificant Remarks, and the Tediouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Conſequent thereupon; as alſo, becauſe there are many Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencies
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:173120:32"/> of your Diſſertation, that I exceedingly concur with you in; As the Deteſtation of what ever comes near, or hath any Allyance with the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> or what you call <hi>Pr ſt Craft,</hi> and Secular Intereſt in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhelters Ignorance, or Sloth, or Covers Implicit Faith and Blind Obedience in the Profeſſors of Chriſtianity: All that ſpeaks Humbleſt Adorations of the Divine Majeſty, and gives Glory to the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and to the Supreme Light of it; and the True Reaſon Flowing from Him, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in and throughout, I moſt Humbly Joyn in; Tho I acknowledg there is great Reaſon of Caution when the Deſignation of Goſpel-Truth is not Univerſal, and Uniform; Leaſt there be an <hi>Advantage</hi> given to the Prince of Darkneſs or any of his Artifices, becauſe of ſome Flaſhes of an <hi>Angel of Light</hi> from Him: Or a bidding good Speed to thoſe, who Bring not <hi>this Doctrine; viz.</hi> of <hi>The Son of God,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſtiles it. 2 <hi>John</hi> 10. Laſtly, I have not been Minute in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions of your Periods, becauſe there are many things, that fly off from the Principal Matter; And it is of no concernment to what is Principal in my Eye, whether they are one way, or other.</p>
            <p>I have therefore made it my Aim, and I hope, it hath been my Buſineſs to Diſcover (as I may ſay) the <hi>Foundation to the very Neck.</hi> And in theſe Things I have Eſpecially placed my main intention, and my <hi>Argumentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To uphold the Honour, Glory and Authority of the Stile of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> in the word, <hi>Mystery:</hi> Fitted by it ſelf to its own Revelations; and that it may not be waved or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved from upon any Forreign Suggeſtions; nor particularly on that very weak one, pardon me, in ſo plainly Expreſſing it; that becauſe it Names the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity;</hi> and that on the <hi>Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Babylon,</hi> there was <hi>written, Myſtery;</hi> 
               <q>Note, that <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> is made the Diſtinguiſhing mark of the Falſe or <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Church;</hi> and therefore; that as Far, as any Church allows of <hi>Myſteries,</hi> ſo far it is <hi>Antichriſtian,</hi> and may with a great deal of Juſtice, tho little Honour, claim Kindred with the <hi>Scarlet Whore:</hi>
               </q> If this be not the Argument of one Driven to Shifts I know not what is! Who muſt not of neceſſity infer, if the once mentioning the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> and once more, <hi>Myſtery on the Forehead of</hi> Babylon, can be ſo ſuppoſed to the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, and Diſhonour of <hi>Myſtery,</hi> the ſo often Recording it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:173120:32"/> for the Honour of the Goſpel, and of the Doctrines of it muſt not be much more to the <hi>Glory of the Word and Thing, Myſtery?</hi> and that the other Naming of it, was not indeed to the diſhonour of it, but of that <hi>Iniquity</hi> only, to which it is Joyned: And further, Is it not plain? That the <hi>Myſtery</hi> of <hi>Iniquity,</hi> is a <hi>Counter Myſtery to the Myſtery of Godlineſs?</hi> And that the <hi>Counter Mystery</hi> were nothing, if the Grand <hi>Myſtery,</hi> did not ſuper-Exiſt to it; <hi>Even as Antichriſt is to Chriſt, and Antichriſtianiſm is to Chriſtianiſm;</hi> ſo is the <hi>Mystery of Iniquity,</hi> to the <hi>Myſtery of Godlineſs; Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſm</hi> hath not ſo much as a ſhaddow of Appearance without that great Subſtance, <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> nor <hi>Antichriſt without, The Chriſt;</hi> the Former infers the Latter; and it might be as well ſaid, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity</hi> is a Note of a <hi>Falſe Church,</hi> becauſe Antichriſtianiſm hath any Allyance of <hi>Sound,</hi> or ſo much, as that ſound implies of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to it; or that it were the Note of a Falſe <hi>Chriſt;</hi> That <hi>Antichriſt</hi> hath the laſt Syllable of his Name from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as that the <hi>mystery of Godlineſs</hi> is ſo, becauſe the <hi>myſtery of Iniquity</hi> is out of all doubt the mark of the <hi>Falſe Church.</hi> Whereas indeed, the dark ſide of the Pillar in Each, is a demonſtration of the other ſide full of Light, and Glory: This therefore could no way de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve to be among the Enlargements of the Second Edition which ought to be upon Refinement of Thoughts; and yet it is found, p. 107. of the Second Edition.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I have been ſo zealous of <hi>mystery,</hi> leaſt any of the Great Doctrines of the Goſpel ſhould be Clandeſtinely withdrawn un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Pretenſion of <hi>Chriſtianity not myſterious;</hi> that is, If <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> as it is now ſo Fallen, Co rupted, and even Detruncated (but as Reſtor'd by the Supreme Reaſon) cannot pleaſe it ſelf in any of the great Truths of the Goſpel, It ſhould be Rejected; and herein I have eſpecial Regard to that great Doctrine of the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the Word,</hi> (who is the only <hi>Begotten Son of the Father</hi>) the <hi>Spirit, Who are One, The One God;</hi> and to the Redemption of Jeſus Chriſt by the Sacrifice Offered by the <hi>Eternal Spirit.</hi> As I have at more full debated in the Anſwer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I have eſpecially deſired, that the Scripture Word, and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Myſtery</hi> may be Conſidered, as it ſhews the neceſſity of Dependence upon the Divine Grace, upon the conſtant Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendency of the <hi>Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation;</hi> For that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always in the Hearts of his Servants a <hi>Spirit of Wiſdom and Revelation,</hi> Enlightning them into the great Truths of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:173120:33"/> they muſt according, even to the Acknowledgment of the Author be <hi>Myſtery,</hi> becauſe a continual Internal Revelation is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary not only to the Firſt Reception, but to the Progreſſion of Chriſtians; their <hi>growing in Grace,</hi> and in the <hi>Knowledge of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> Which great conſideration I would moſt Humbly, and yet moſi Affectionately Recommend to the Author, with All his Favourers; That ſeeing they ſeem to Re-due ſo much to <hi>Sacred Oracles,</hi> They would with all ſeriouſneſs conſider theſe great Words, <hi>Grace, Free-Grace, Gifts from above, Wiſdom from the Father of Lights,</hi> and Exchange that ſo Admired Word, <hi>Reaſon,</hi> as it is now, or as Human, for that Adorable word, <hi>Grace;</hi> that they would Attently Contemplate the Cenſure of the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in his Word upon all Human Intellectuals, till there be a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novation in the Spirit of the mind;</hi> and this would moſt eaſily Conciliate to Them the True Scripture-Notion of <hi>Myſtery:</hi> And ſeeing the Author hath Promiſed an Undeceiving of thoſe whom he ſuppoſes Deceived, concerning the Illumination, and Efficaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Operation of the Divine Spirit; I deſire of Him to have a Particular Regard herein to my ſelf, how Triflng or Abſur'd an Adverſary ſoever I may appear to him; And that he would do it in the meekneſs of the Spirit of Chriſtianity, reſpecting only the Subſtance, and Merits of the Point, and of what I have ſaid; I find nothing further in the Enlargements of the <hi>Second Edition,</hi> that I have not conſidered in the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the Firſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beſeeching the conducts of the Spirit of Truth into All Truth; and that the Greater Proportions of Reaſon, or Intellectuals, and Elocution, the Author, or any of his Friends have; the more they may aſcribe, and dedicate themſelves to the Supreme <hi>Reaſon</hi> and his <hi>Grace,</hi> This ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
               <signed>In All Truly Chriſtian Offices, Your Friend and Servant, <hi>T.B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>Pardon ſome ſmaller miſtakes, particularly, P. 1. Margin, read <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, l. ult. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 14. after <hi>Egypt,</hi> put in <hi>to.</hi> P. 16. l. 23. before <hi>Affirm,</hi> put in <hi>whereof they.</hi> P. 46. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:173120:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
